<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>Contact Addresses for XMPP Services</title>
  <abstract>This document defines a method for specifying contact addresses related to an XMPP service.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0157</number>
  <status>Proposed</status>
  <type>Informational</type>
  <jig>Standards JIG</jig>
  <approver>Council</approver>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>N/A</shortname>
  &stpeter;
  <author>
    <firstname>Jacek</firstname>
    <surname>Konieczny</surname>
    <email>jajcus@jajcus.net</email>
    <jid>jajcus@jabber.bnet.pl</jid>
  </author>
  <revision>
    <version>0.3</version>
    <date>2006-07-31</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Recommended support for RFC2142-style mailbox in addition to XMPP address.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.2</version>
    <date>2006-07-18</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Removed extended addressing recommendations pending further review.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <date>2005-09-08</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Initial version.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.2</version>
    <date>2005-09-06</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added security considerations and XMPP Registrar considerations.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2005-08-27</date>
    <initials>psa/jk</initials>
    <remark><p>First draft.</p></remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  &RFC3920BISNOTE;
  <p>&rfc2142; specifies conventional electronic mailbox names for common services, roles, and functions related to SMTP, NNTP, and HTTP (such as postmaster@domain.tld, usenet@domain.tld, and webmaster@domain.tld). However, no such conventional email address or XMPP address (JID) has been specified for XMPP services. This document remedies that oversight.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Address' anchor='xmpp'>
  <p>Many existing Jabber/XMPP server implementations use the bare domain of the server as an alias for the server administrator(s), such that a &MESSAGE; stanza addressed to that domain name (e.g., "jabber.org") is delivered to the JIDs of the server administrator(s). <note>This does not apply to &IQ; or &PRESENCE; stanzas.</note> An XMPP server implementation SHOULD support this functionality. A domain that provides such functionality MAY also advertise the service through an XMPP URI (see &rfc4622;) of &lt;xmpp:domain.tld&gt; or (per &xep0147;) &lt;xmpp:domain.tld?message&gt;.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Email Address' anchor='email'>
  <p>Consistent with <cite>RFC 2142</cite>, a domain that offers a Jabber/XMPP service SHOULD provide an Internet mailbox of "XMPP" for inquiries related to that service. A domain that provides such functionality MAY also advertise the service through a Mailto URI (see &rfc2368;) of &lt;mailto:xmpp@domain.tld&gt;.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
  <p>Providing or advertising contact addresses may open those addresses to unwanted communication. Server administrators should balance the need for openness with the desire for control over communication with customers and peers.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
  <p>This document requires no interaction with &IANA;.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <p>This document requires no interaction with the &REGISTRAR;.</p>
</section1>
</xep>
