<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>XMPP over QUIC</title>
  <abstract>This specification defines a procedure to make both c2s and s2s XMPP connections over the QUIC protocol instead of TCP+TLS.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0467</number>
  <status>Experimental</status>
  <type>Standards Track</type>
  <sig>Standards</sig>
  <approver>Council</approver>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0156</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0368</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>NOT_YET_ASSIGNED</shortname>
  &moparisthebest;
  <revision>
    <version>0.1.0</version>
    <date>2022-07-13</date>
    <initials>XEP Editor (jsc)</initials>
    <remark>Accepted by vote of Council on 2022-06-22.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2022-06-13</date>
    <initials>tjb</initials>
    <remark><p>First draft.</p></remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  <p>&xmppcore; specifies the use of STARTTLS to connect to an XMPP server. &xep0368; extends that to skip STARTTLS by doing Direct TLS. This XEP defines how to negotiate a XMPP connection over QUIC (&rfc9000;), which provides identical security and authentication to TCP+TLS, along with a number of other desirable properties, such as connection migration across IP changes, and multiple independent bidirectional streams in one session, among others.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Requirements' anchor='reqs'>
    <p>QUIC session negotiation is virtually identical to TLS. This document specifies that the following additional rules apply:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>While other forms of discovery like &xep0156; can discover QUIC connections, we also define UDP port 443 as the default port to attempt a XMPP-over-QUIC connection on if those are not available, yes this is the reserved port for HTTPS, no we don't care because SNI and ALPN are required so there will be no mishaps.</li>
      <li>TLS certificates MUST be validated the same way as for STARTTLS. (i.e., as specified in &xmppcore;).</li>
      <li>STARTTLS MUST NOT be used over QUIC connections.</li>
      <li>Client or server MUST set SNI TLS extension to the JID's domain part, and MUST use &tls-ech; if available.</li>
      <li>Client or server MUST set the ALPN (&rfc7301;) TLS extension, and MUST use &tls-ech; if available.</li>
      <li>The ALPN protocol MUST be '<strong>xmpp-client</strong>' when negotiating an c2s connection.</li>
      <li>The ALPN protocol MUST be '<strong>xmpp-server</strong>' when negotiating an s2s connection.</li>
      <li>The client or server MUST use <link url='https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc9000#section-9'>QUIC Connection Migration</link> which allows for a single QUIC session and therefore multiple XMPP connections to migrate between IPs without reconnecting. The timeout SHOULD be set to the maximum 600 seconds.</li>
      <li>QUIC supports uni-directional and bi-directional streams, but XMPP MUST only use bi-directional streams. Multiple bi-directional MAY be opened in one session after authentication (for S2S) or resource binding (C2S), and MUST be treated with the same security and authentication as negotiated in the initial XMLStream.</li>
    </ol>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Use Cases' anchor='usecases'>
  <section2 topic="Connection Migration">
    <p>The entire QUIC connection can be migrated to a different source IP address. This allows mobile devices to seamlessly switch between mobile data and WiFi, without renegotiation. This takes the place of the session resumption in &xep0198;, which MUST NOT be used.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic="Multiple Streams">
    <p>QUIC allows the use of multiple streams. A QUIC connection still maps to a single XMLStream, and the initial bidirection stream (id=0) SHALL be used to setup and make ready this XMLStream. Until the XMLStream is ready for general stanza exchange, further bidirectional QUIC streams MUST NOT be opened. For S2S XMLStreams, this will be after SASL authentication, whereas for C2S XMLStreams this will be after resource binding. It is advised to support &xep0388; and &xep0387; to streamline these, though there is no interoperability issue if the older forms are used.</p>
    <p>Once multiple streams are opened, it is MANDATORY that both peers continue to follow the ordering rules defined in Section 10.1 of &rfc6120;, however stanzas sent in different QUIC streams have no fixed order relative to those sent in other QUIC streams. The sending peer MUST therefore use a single QUIC stream for all stanzas sent between a pair of two bare jids. For example, when sending a stanza from sender@example.net/resource to receiver@example.com, and another from sender@example.net/other to receiver@sender.com/xyzzy, both stanzas MUST be sent within the same QUIC stream. Multiple "pairs" of Jids MAY share the same QUIC stream, with the degenerate case - all pairs sharing the same QUIC stream - being the case where no additional QUIC streams are opened. This mapping of bare jid pairs to QUIC streams MUST NOT be enforced by the receiver; the receiver MUST simply process all stanzas received over a QUIC stream in the order they were sent in the same way they would if a single QUIC stream (or TCP) were used.</p>
    <p>In the C2S case, all stanzas sent to the user's own bare jid and also to the server's jid itself MUST be sent on the same QUIC stream, and this SHOULD be the initial stream (id=0).</p>
    <p>Top Level Elements other than Stanzas, such as CSI, stream errors, etc, MUST be sent on the initial stream (id=0) only.</p>
    <p>There is no "stream open" or "stream close" sent on streams other than the initial stream (id=0).</p>
    <p>There is no requirement that the peer use the same QUIC streams for the same bare jid pairs, though again in C2S the initial stream (id=0) SHOULD be used for all stanzas sent from the user's own bare jid and also from the server's jid itself. In the general case, though, this means that (for example) an &lt;iq type='result'/> MAY come back on a different QUIC stream than the &lt;iq type='get'/> that elicited it.</p>
    <p>Conceptually, there remains a single XMLStream for an entire QUIC connection, and the XMLStream state therefore applies to all QUIC streams within the QUIC connection. Stanzas received on a QUIC stream are processed by taking each complete stanza and injecting it into the XMLStream at that point. An incomplete stanza received on any QUIC stream (including the initial stream) is buffered until such time as the data arrives to complete it.</p>
    <p>The benefits of doing this are that individual streams do not block each other on low bandwidth or packet loss. Eliminating this blocking effect, called Head Of Line Blocking, means that higher-volume chatrooms (for example) do not slow down the transmission of perhaps more urgent low volume messages. Because of this effect, peers MAY use QUIC's ability to proritise specific QUIC streams for finer control, though this is out of scope for this document.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic="Stream Management">
    <p>Because of multiple streams, the state of the XMLStream cannot be captured with a simple counter. This means that &xep0198; cannot apply to QUIC connections, and &xep0198; MUST NOT be advertised or negotiated. Luckily, QUIC provides its own mechanism equivalent to resumption. For stanza-level acknowledgements, however, there is no equivalent immediately available.</p>
    <p>Open Question: What do we do instead? A lighter &lt;a xmlns='urn:xmpp:quic:0'/> perhaps? Or do we build something more heavyweight which just handles stanza acknowledgements, but includes MAM ids etc?</p>
  </section2>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
    <p>QUIC provides AT LEAST the same level of security as STARTTLS and Direct TLS, and far more privacy with &tls-ech; (which can and should be used with Direct TLS, but this isn't a MUST). QUIC provides more security than STARTTLS if &rfc7590; is not followed, as it isn't subject to STARTTLS stripping. All security setup and certificate validation code SHOULD be shared between the QUIC, STARTTLS and Direct TLS logic as well.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
<p>ALPN (&rfc7301;) requires registration of new Protocol IDs.  This document re-uses the two Protocol IDs specified in &xep0368;, but the ALPN registry (currently located <link url='https://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-extensiontype-values/tls-extensiontype-values.xhtml#alpn-protocol-ids'>here</link>) should be updated to additionally point to this document.</p>

<p>IANA requires registration of port numbers too (currently located <link url='https://www.iana.org/assignments/service-names-port-numbers/service-names-port-numbers.xhtml'>here</link>) but UDP 443 is already assigned to HTTPS, which also requires ALPN, so I think no registration is required.</p>

</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <p>This document requires no interaction with the &REGISTRAR;.</p>
</section1>
</xep>
