<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
        <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
        %ents;
        ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>Anonymous unique occupant identifiers for MUCs</title>
  <abstract>This specification defines a method that allows clients to identify a MUC participant across reconnects and renames. It thus prevents impersonification of anonymous users.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0421</number>
  <status>Experimental</status>
  <type>Standards Track</type>
  <sig>Standards</sig>
  <approver>Council</approver>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0001</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0030</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0045</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>occupant-id</shortname>
  <author>
    <firstname>Marvin</firstname>
    <surname>Wissfeld</surname>
    <email>xsf@larma.de</email>
    <jid>jabber@larma.de</jid>
  </author>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1.0</version>
    <date>2019-08-20</date>
    <initials>XEP Editor (jsc)</initials>
    <remark>Accepted by vote of Council on 2019-07-17.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2019-07-13</date>
    <initials>mw</initials>
    <remark><p>First draft.</p></remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  <p>
    &xep0045; allows the creation of semi-anonymous multi-user text chats where
    the real JID of a occupant can not be discovered by other MUC
    occupants except moderators. As such users can freely join with using
    any identity of their choice, allowing to impersonate users while they are
    not online.
  </p>
  <p>
    With recent standard extensions, it becomes more relevant to be able to
    know if the occupant that sends one message is the same as the sender
    of another message, for example for &xep0308;. At the same time it becomes
    harder for clients to determine this, for example due to the use of &xep0313;
    with MUCs.
  </p>
  <p>
    This specification defines a method to combat issues arising out of the
    anonymity of MUC occupants while at the same time ensuring their privacy
    by not leaking their real JID to other occupants.
  </p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Discovering support' anchor='disco'>
  <p>
    If a MUC implements anonymous unique occupant identifiers, it MUST
    specify the 'urn:xmpp:occupant-id:0' feature in its service discovery
    information features as specified in &xep0030;.
  </p>
  <example caption='Client requests information about a MUC'><![CDATA[
<iq type='get'
    to='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit'
    from='hag66@shakespeare.lit/pda'
    id='info1'>
  <query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'/>
</iq>]]></example>
  <example caption='MUC advertises support for anonymous unique occupant identifiers'><![CDATA[
<iq type='result'
    to='hag66@shakespeare.lit/pda'
    from='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit'
    id='info1'>
  <query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'>
...
    <feature var='urn:xmpp:occupant-id:0'/>
...
  </query>
</iq>]]></example>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Use Cases' anchor='usecases'>
  <section2 topic="Entering a Room" anchor="enter">
    <p>
      When a user enters a room, they send a presence to claim the nickname in
      the MUC. A MUC that supports anonymous unique occupant identifiers
      attaches an &lt;occupant-id&gt; element to the presence sent to all
      occupants in the room.
    </p>
    <example caption="Client sends a message"><![CDATA[
<presence
    from='hag66@shakespeare.lit/pda'
    id='n13mt3l'
    to='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit/thirdwitch'>
  <x xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/muc'/>
</presence>]]></example>
    <example caption="Service Sends New Occupant's Presence to All Occupants"><![CDATA[
<presence
    from='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit/thirdwitch'
    id='27C55F89-1C6A-459A-9EB5-77690145D624'
    to='crone1@shakespeare.lit/desktop'>
  <x xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/muc#user' />
  <occupant-id xmlns="urn:xmpp:occupant-id:0" id="dd72603deec90a38ba552f7c68cbcc61bca202cd" />
</presence>]]></example>
  </section2>
    <section2 topic="Sending a Message to All Occupants" anchor="message">
      <p>
        An occupant sends a message to all other occupants in the room by
        sending a message of type "groupchat" to the &lt;room@service&gt;. A MUC
        supporting anonymous unique occupant identifiers attaches an
        &lt;occupant-id&gt; element to the message sent to all occupants in the
        room.
      </p>
    <example caption="Occupant Sends a Message to All Occupants"><![CDATA[
<message
    from='hag66@shakespeare.lit/pda'
    id='hysf1v37'
    to='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit'
    type='groupchat'>
  <body>Harpier cries: 'tis time, 'tis time.</body>
</message>]]></example>
    <example caption="Service Reflects Message to All Occupants"><![CDATA[
<message
    from='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit/thirdwitch'
    id='hysf1v37'
    to='crone1@shakespeare.lit/desktop'
    type='groupchat'>
  <body>Harpier cries: 'tis time, 'tis time.</body>
  <occupant-id xmlns="urn:xmpp:occupant-id:0" id="dd72603deec90a38ba552f7c68cbcc61bca202cd" />
</message>]]></example>
  </section2>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Business Rules' anchor='rules'>
  <p>
    Messages and presences MUST NOT contain more then one &lt;occupant-id&gt;
    element. If the message or presence received by the MUC service already
    contains &lt;occupant-id&gt; element, the MUC service MUST replace such
    element before reflecting the message or presence including it.
  </p>
  <p>
    The &lt;occupant-id&gt; element MUST be attached to every message and every
    presence sent by a MUC. This includes messages sent as part of the
    discussion history after joining a room, requested via &xep0313; or any
    other means.
  </p>
  <p>
    The &lt;occupant-id&gt; element MUST be ignored if support for the feature
    is not announced via &xep0030;, as malicious clients might forge occupant
    identifiers if the room does not support them.
  </p>
  <p>
    A MUC service MAY allow the administrator to enable or disable occupant
    identifiers on a per-room basis. If occupant identifiers are force enabled
    for all rooms on a MUC service, it SHOULD additionally specify the 
    'urn:xmpp:occupant-id:0' feature on the MUC service. It MUST NOT specify
    the feature on the service otherwise.
  </p>
  <section2 topic='Occupant ID generation' anchor='id-generation'>
    <p>
      The occupant identifier MUST be generated such that it is stable. This
      means that if a user joins the same room a second time, the occupant
      identifier MUST be the same as was assigned the first time. A user in
      the sense of this specification is identified by its real bare JID.
    </p>
    <p>
      The occupant identifier MUST be generated such that it is unique. This
      means that it MUST be sufficiently improbable that one user is able to
      re-create the occupant identifier of another user.
    </p>
    <p>
      The occupant identifier MUST be generated such that it is anonymous. This
      means that it MUST be sufficiently hard to determine the real bare JID of
      an occupant from its occupant identifier. Additionally, a MUC service
      SHOULD generate the identifier such that the occupant identifier of a user
      in one room of the service does not match the occupant identifier of the
      same user in another room of the same service.
    </p>
    <p>
      The occupant identifier MUST have a maximum length of 128 characters. The
      recipient MUST consider the occupant identifier to be an opaque string.
    </p>
    <p>
      One way to ensure these properties is to generate a private secret key for
      every room and use an HMAC algorithm with a sufficiently secure hash
      function to generate the occupant identifier from the real bare JID and
      that secret key. This procedure ensures all the required properties with
      minimal server side storage requirements.
    </p>
  </section2>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
  <p>
    If a MUC uses occupant identifiers, nickname changes will be visible to
    all occupants of the room. Clients MAY warn users about this circumstance
    before joining the room.
  </p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
  <p>This document requires no interaction with &IANA;.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <section2 topic='Protocol Namespaces' anchor='ns'>
    <p>The &REGISTRAR; includes 'urn:xmpp:occupant-id:0' in its registry of protocol namespaces (see &NAMESPACES;).</p>
    <ul>
      <li>urn:xmpp:occupant-id:0</li>
    </ul>
  </section2>
</section1>
</xep>
