<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "xep.ent">
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>Compliance JIG</title>
  <abstract>A proposal to form a JIG devoted to issues related to protocol compliance.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0069</number>
  <status>Deferred</status>
  <type>JIG Formation</type>
  <jig>None</jig>
  <author>
    <firstname>Peter</firstname>
    <surname>Saint-Andre</surname>
    <email>stpeter@jabber.org</email>
    <jid>stpeter@jabber.org</jid>
  </author>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <date>2003-01-29</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Initial release</remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction'>
  <p>The Jabber Software Foundation has an initiative underway to define and implement compliance testing of software that is based on XMPP and JSF-approved protocols. To date, participation in this compliance program has been limited to elected members of the JSF. However, not all matters related to the compliance program need to be limited to JSF members. In particular, it would be valuable to receive community feedback and input regarding test plans, testing software, and the like. In order to broaden participation, we propose that the JSF form a standing Jabber Interest Group devoted to compliance.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Scope and Role'>
  <p>The Compliance JIG shall provide a public forum for discussion and development of systems for testing compliance with the protocols defined and accepted by the JSF. It shall not have ultimate accountability for the JSF compliance program; rather, that accountability shall rest with the members-only Compliance Team. The Compliance JIG shall act in an advisory capacity in relation to the Compliance Team. In essence, the relationship between the Compliance JIG and the Compliance Team is analagous to the relationship between the Standards JIG and the Jabber Council.</p>
  <p>In particular, the Compliance JIG shall work with the Compliance Team to define the processes, standards, test cases, and testing software required by the compliance program. However, the Compliance JIG shall not be privy to actual testing results, which shall be available only to the Compliance Team.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Membership'>
  <p>The Compliance JIG shall be open to the public and shall not be limited to elected members of the Jabber Software Foundation. Compliance JIG discussions shall be conducted on a dedicated mailing list &lt;compliance-jig@jabber.org&gt; as well as in the &lt;foundation@conference.jabber.org&gt; chatroom.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Lifetime'>
  <p>The Compliance JIG shall be a standing JIG, and shall exist as long as the JSF compliance program is in operation.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Deliverables'>
  <p>The Compliance JIG shall produce at least the following deliverables:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Documentation of the testing process</li>
    <li>Compliance test plans</li>
    <li>Compliance testing software</li>
    <li>Logo requirements</li>
  </ul>
</section1>
</xep>
