<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>XMPP Registrar</title>
  <abstract>This document defines the roles and processes of the XMPP Registrar within the Jabber Software Foundation.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0053</number>
  <status>Active</status>
  <type>Procedural</type>
  <jig>None</jig>
  <approver>Board</approver>
  <dependencies/>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>N/A</shortname>
  &stpeter;
  <revision>
    <version>1.2</version>
    <date>2006-10-04</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>As approved by the members of the Jabber Software Foundation, changed Jabber Registrar to XMPP Registrar.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>1.1</version>
    <date>2004-05-20</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Updated to reflect experience.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <date>2003-03-20</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Per a vote of the XMPP Council, advanced status to Active.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.5</version>
    <date>2003-01-21</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Changed name to XMPP Registrar in response to feedback from the JSF Board of Directors.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.4</version>
    <date>2003-01-20</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Added reference to jana@jabber.org mailing list.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.3</version>
    <date>2002-11-22</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Simplified to reflect discussion in the XMPP Council; in particular, reserved JANA functions to the XMPP Extensions Editor until there is a perceived need for a more formal governing body.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.2</version>
    <date>2002-10-27</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Clarified JANA composition, panel member requirements, and JANA process.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <date>2002-10-24</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Initial version.</remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction and Purpose'>
  <p>As the &JSF; publishes more protocol specifications (see &xep0001;), it becomes necessary to keep better track of the namespaces defined by those specifications as well as the parameters used in the context of the relevant protocols. (Examples of such parameters include the features and options used in &xep0020; and the identities and features used in &xep0030;.) In particular, the common use of protocols published by the JSF requires that namespaces and particular parameter values be assigned uniquely. It is the role of the XMPP Registrar to make those unique assignments and to maintain registries of the currently assigned values. The XMPP Registrar shall also function as a single point of contact between the Jabber/XMPP developer community and &IANA;.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Composition'>
  <p>Until there is a perceived need for a more formal governing body, the functions of the XMPP Registrar shall be managed by the &EDITOR;. In the future, the &COUNCIL; and/or the &BOARD; may decide to create a more formal panel to oversee the functions of the XMPP Registrar; if they do, this document shall be updated to reflect the change.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Process'>
  <p>Every XMPP Extension Protocol specification (XEP) must contain a section devoted to "XMPP Registrar Considerations", detailing the namespaces and parameters to be registered with the XMPP Registrar, as well as any new registries to be created as a result of the XEP.</p>
  <p>The registry additions or creations specified in an XMPP Extension Protocol specification shall not take effect until the document advances to a status of Draft (Standards-Track XEPs) or Active (Informational and Historical XEPs). Registration of namespaces shall be initiated by the XMPP Extensions Editor when a XEP advances to Draft or Active and shall not require the involvement of the document author. Registration of particular parameters used within a specification shall be initiated by the XMPP Extensions Editor if specified in the XEP, and may also be initiated by implementors of the XMPP Extension Protocol document after it has advanced to Active, Draft, or Final. Creation of new registries shall be initiated by the XMPP Registrar; if a document specifies the creation of a new registry, the author is strongly encouraged to consult with the XMPP Registrar before seeking a Last Call on the XEP.</p>
  <p>Requests for namespace and parameter assignments must be sent to the XMPP Registrar in accordance with the process specified in the document (usually a XEP) that defines the relevant registry, normally by sending an appropriately formatted email message to &lt;registrar@jabber.org&gt;. If, in the Registrar's judgment, discussion of a request is required, the Registrar shall initiate such discussion within the &SJIG;. The Registrar shall add registry items at his discretion based on discussion within the Standards JIG if necessary, but shall not unduly restrict registration of parameter values. If a document author or implementer thinks that a request was unfairly denied by the Registrar, an appeal of the decision may be directed to the XMPP Council.</p>
  <p>The XMPP Registrar shall maintain registries of assigned namespaces and parameters at &lt;<link url="http://www.xmpp.org/registrar/">http://www.xmpp.org/registrar/</link>&gt; and shall update those registries in a timely fashion. Changes to JSF registries shall be announced on the Standards-JIG mailing list.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Security Considerations'>
  <p>Security considerations are primarily the responsibility of the protocols in which specific parameters are used. The XMPP Registrar shall respect the security considerations defined in JSF protocol specifications, and shall endeavor to ensure that registered parameter values do not compromise privacy or security in any way.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='IANA Considerations'>
  <p>The XMPP Registrar shall be responsible for interacting with the IANA on behalf of the Jabber Software Foundation and Jabber/XMPP developer community. If an XMPP Extension Protocol document requires interaction with the IANA, that fact shall be noted by the document author and discussed on the Standards-JIG mailing list along with normal discussion of the XEP. The XMPP Registrar shall collaborate with the author to present an appropriate request to the IANA.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations'>
  <p>This entire document defines the processes and procedures of the XMPP Registrar.</p>
</section1>
</xep>
