<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>XMPP Server Compliance 2009</title>
  <abstract>This document defines XMPP server compliance levels for 2009.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0243</number>
  <status>Proposed</status>
  <type>Standards Track</type>
  <sig>Standards</sig>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
    <spec>XMPP IM</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0016</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0030</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0045</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0054</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0124</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0138</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0163</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0191</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0206</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>N/A</shortname>
  &stpeter;
  <revision>
    <version>0.3</version>
    <date>2008-07-16</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added PEP as required for Advanced level per Council discussion.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.2</version>
    <date>2008-06-18</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Changed compliance level names, updated required support per Council discussion.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <date>2008-05-28</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Initial published version, incorporating Council feedback.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2009-05-27</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>First draft, copied and modified from XEP-0212.</p></remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  <p>The &XSF; defines protocol suites for the purpose of compliance testing and software certification. This document specifies the 2009 compliance levels for XMPP servers. Support for the listed specifications is REQUIRED for compliance purposes.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Core Server 2009' anchor='core'>
  <p>The XMPP Core Server 2009 certification level is defined below. Support for these specifications is REQUIRED for compliance purposes.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>&rfc3920; *</li>
    <li>&rfc3921; *</li>
    <li>&xep0030;</li>
  </ul>
  <p>* Note: RFC 3920 and RFC 3921 are currently being revised to correct errors, clarify matters that were underspecified, and incorporate feedback based on implementation and deployment experience gained since RFC 3920 and RFC 3921 were published in 2004. Although the compliance level specified herein refers to RFC 3920 and RFC 3921, developers are also advised to consult &rfc3920bis; and &rfc3921bis;, which provide the most up-to-date and accurate description the core XMPP protocols.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Advanced Server 2009' anchor='advanced'>
  <p>The XMPP Advanced Server 2009 certification level is defined as follows:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>XMPP Core Server 2009 (see above)</li>
    <li>&xep0016; and &xep0191;</li>
    <li>&xep0045; (support may be enabled via an external component or an internal server module/plugin)</li>
    <li>&xep0054;</li>
    <li>&xep0124; and &xep0206; (support may be enabled via an external component or an internal server module/plugin)</li>
    <li>&xep0163;</li>
  </ul>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Implementation Notes' anchor='impl'>
  <p>Some of the protocol specifications referenced herein have their own dependencies; developers must refer to the relevant specifications for further information.</p>
  <p>Developers are advised to refer to &xep0178; regarding proper implementation of the SASL EXTERNAL mechanism in XMPP.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
  <p>This document introduces no additional security considerations above and beyond those defined in the documents on which it depends.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
  <p>This document requires no interaction with &IANA;.</p> 
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <p>This document requires no interaction with the &REGISTRAR;.</p> 
</section1>
</xep>
