<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep><header>
<title>No-reply JIDs</title>
<abstract>This specification defines a way for JIDs to advertise that they don’t accept incoming chat messages.</abstract>
&LEGALNOTICE;
<number>0506</number>
<status>Experimental</status>
<type>Standards Track</type>
<sig>Standards</sig>
<approver>Council</approver>
<dependencies>
<spec>XMPP Core</spec>
<spec>XEP-0030</spec>
<spec>XEP-0115</spec>
</dependencies>
<supersedes/>
<supersededby/>
<shortname>no-reply</shortname>
<author>
<firstname>Matthew</firstname>
<surname>Wild</surname>
<email>mwild1@gmail.com</email>
</author>
<revision>
  <version>0.1.0</version>
  <date>2025-10-20</date>
  <initials>dg</initials>
  <remark>Accepted as Experimental by council vote</remark>
</revision>
<revision>
<version>0.0.1</version>
<date>2025-10-08</date>
<initials>mw</initials>
<remark>
<p>Initial submission.</p>
</remark>
</revision>
</header>
<section1 topic="Introduction" anchor="intro">

<p>This protocol defines a way for a JID to advertise that it does not accept incoming chat messages. For example, automated services which broadcast messages.</p>

<p>Such an indication allows clients to adapt their user interface accordingly (for example, hiding message input controls), instead of allowing the user to send a message and receive errors. This can improve the user experience and avoid confusion.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Requirements" anchor="reqs">

<ul>
<li>The protocol should not require clients to perform additional queries.</li>
</ul>

</section1><section1 topic="Use Cases" anchor="usecases">

<p>One example use case for this protocol, would be a server which sends welcome messages or other announcements (maintenance, etc.) to its users from its own JID (e.g. 'example.com').</p>

<p>To show that users should not reply to messages sent from this JID, the server advertises <tt>urn:xmpp:noreply:0</tt> in the &xep0030; features of that JID (i.e. 'example.com') to indicate this to the clients.</p>

<p>In most cases it is expected that the recipient will learn of the feature using &xep0115; rather than performing service discovery just to learn of the no-reply feature. In the case of a server’s JID, the entity capabilities are typically communicated to the client in the initial stream features.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Business Rules" anchor="business-rules">

<p>Any entity which does not accept chat messages should advertise the service discovery feature:</p>

<ul>
<li><tt>urn:xmpp:noreply:0</tt></li>
</ul>

<p>In the case that a full JID advertises the no-reply feature, and there are other resources of the same JID which do not advertise the feature, a client SHOULD NOT prevent the user from sending messages (e.g. to other resources or to the bare JID).</p>

<p>Advertising the no-reply feature indicates that a JID does not accept messages. If a JID does accept messages, even if it sometimes sends automated messages, it MUST NOT advertise this feature.</p>

<p>If a JID advertises the feature and receives an incoming message anyway (e.g. from a sender that does not support this XEP) then it SHOULD respond with an error, per the usual processing rules of &rfc6120;.</p>

<p>The no-reply feature pertains only to chat messages, such as those typically originated from humans. A JID which advertises this feature MAY accept other kinds of messages (for example, a news bot which advertises this feature would still be expected to receive pubsub notifications even though they are conveyed as messages).</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Accessibility Considerations" anchor="access">

<p>There are no known special accessibility considerations for this protocol.</p>

<p>It is expected that it may improve accessibility by simplifying interfaces where possible.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Security Considerations" anchor="security">

<p>There are no known security considerations for this protocol, beyond those existing in normal service discovery flows.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Privacy Considerations" anchor="privacy">

<p>There are no known privacy considerations for this protocol.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">

<p>This protocol does not require any interaction with IANA.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="XMPP Registrar Considerations" anchor="registrar">

<p>This document registers the following service discovery feature:</p>

<ul>
<li><tt>urn:xmpp:noreply:0</tt></li>
</ul>

</section1><section1 topic="Design Considerations" anchor="design">

<p>It was debated whether to include the no-reply indication on a per JID, presence or message basis. As most chat clients show an interface featuring an input control per remote JID, and due to the potential optimization afforded by XEP-0115, it was decided to use service discovery.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="XML Schema" anchor="schema">

<p>This document defines no new XML elements or attributes.</p>
</section1>
</xep>

