<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
        <!ENTITY ns "urn:xmpp:fulltext:0">
        <!ENTITY nsx "urn:example:">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>Full Text Search in MAM</title>
  <abstract>This specification proposes a field in the MAM form for full text searching.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0431</number>
  <status>Deferred</status>
  <type>Standards Track</type>
  <sig>Standards</sig>
  <approver>Council</approver>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0313</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>fulltextmam</shortname>
  &dcridland;
  <revision>
    <version>0.2.0</version>
    <date>2020-01-29</date>
    <initials>dwd</initials>
    <remark>
      <ul>
        <li>No More Beer</li>
        <li>Quasi-normative language around syntactic implementation</li>
      </ul>
    </remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1.0</version>
    <date>2020-01-29</date>
    <initials>XEP Editor (jsc)</initials>
    <remark>Accepted by vote of Council on 2020-01-22.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2020-01-21</date>
    <initials>dwd</initials>
    <remark>
      <ul>
        <li>Initial Revision</li>
      </ul>
    </remark>
  </revision>
</header>

<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  <p>&xep0313; has an extensible form. This specification extends the extensible form with an extension which extends MAM to perform full text searching. A number of existing implementations of this extension exist - extending their existing extensions to confirm to the extension in this specification now it exists is intended to be trivial.</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic='Overview' anchor="overview">
  <section2 topic="Discovering Support" anchor="feature">
    <p>Support for this protocol is advertised by the Service Discovery protocol defined in &xep0030; using a feature
      of <tt>&ns;</tt>.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic="Searching">
    <p>Searching using full text is performed by the client supplying an additional text key, which if non-empty is used as input to a full text search of some form. The precise meaning of this field is left entirely implementation-defined at this time. Future revisions of this specification might impose additional constraints.</p>
  </section2>
</section1>

  <section1 topic="Protocol Elements">
    <section2 topic="Querying">
      <p>A text input field of <tt>{&ns;}fulltext</tt> is hereby defined for the 'urn:xmpp:mam:2' FORM_TYPE, as conforming to the syntax defined in &xep0068;</p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic="Results">
      <p>The precise matching of the supplied text string is left implementation-defined. Servers MAY use any full-text search mechanism. While this might mean that certain characters are deemed "special", clients are RECOMMENDED not to attempt any support for these, as they are unlikely to be portable between implementations. While many implementations of this protocol might conform in a purely syntactic sense, it is to be noted that the intent is that a reasonable full-text search is performed based on the input - servers SHOULD therefore honour this intent despite the lack of a formal strict definition.</p>
    </section2>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic="Schema">
    <p>Not sure this is needed at all.</p>
  </section1>

<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
  <p>None?</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
  <p>This XEP requires no interaction with &IANA;. </p>
</section1>

<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <p>Registration of the field pointing to this document.</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic='Acknowledgements' anchor='ack'>
  <p>Guus der Kinderen nudged me into doing this. Matthew Wild and Kev Smith argued reasonably that nobody should have to buy beer.</p>
</section1>

</xep>
