<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>Special Interest Groups (SIGs)</title>
  <abstract>A definition of Special Interest Groups within the XMPP Standards Foundation.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0002</number>
  <status>Active</status>
  <type>Procedural</type>
  <sig>None</sig>
  <approver>Board</approver>
  <dependencies/>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>N/A</shortname>
  &stpeter;
  <revision>
    <version>1.1</version>
    <date>2002-01-11</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Clarified some details and added information about cut-offs for inactivity.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <date>2001-06-28</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>First release, modified from Rahul Dave's modification of my original post.</remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Short Definition'>
  <p>A Special Interest Group (SIG) is a working group approved by the XMPP Council to address specific areas of growth or concern within the Jabber/XMPP developer community, usually by means of developing and publishing XMPP Extension Protocols (XEPs).</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Explanation'>
  <p>The main function of most SIGs is to produce acceptable XMPP extensions (delivered in the form of XMPP Extension Protocols or XEPs <note>For information about XMPP Extension Protocols, see <link url="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0001.html">http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0001.html</link>.</note>) within a reasonably limited period of time. However, at the discretion of the XMPP Council, a handful of standing SIGs may be approved (e.g., to address security or standards compliance).</p>
  <p>Anyone (not limited to members of the XMPP Standards Foundation) may propose the formation of a SIG by completing a XMPP Extension Protocol outlining the need for the SIG and its proposed focus. However, SIG leaders must be members of the XMPP Standards Foundation. The number of leaders for a SIG is flexible, and shall be determined by each SIG, in consultation with the XMPP Council if necessary. The concept of "membership" with regard to SIGs is loose, and is essentially co-extensive with membership in the appropriate mailing list (each SIG has its own mailing list, which is archived for public review). SIG members do not need to be members of the XMPP Standards Foundation, and any member of the general public may subscribe to SIG mailing lists.</p>
  <p>It is expected that all SIGs (other than certain standing SIGs) will remain active for as long as necessary in order to produce one or more standards-track specifications for review by the XMPP Council in the SIG's area of focus. However, if a SIG does not show signs of activity for an extended period of time (usually six months of inactivity on the SIG's mailing list), the SIG may be disbanded at the discretion of the XMPP Council with appropriate warning to the SIG members (usually in the form of an email sent to the SIG's mailing list).</p>
</section1>
</xep>
