<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>Data Forms File Input Element</title>
  <abstract>This specification defines an element which can be used with data forms to let users upload one or more files.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0505</number>
  <status>Experimental</status>
  <type>Standards Track</type>
  <sig>Standards</sig>
  <approver>Council</approver>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0004</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0447</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>file-input</shortname>
  <tags>
    <tag>data forms</tag>
    <tag>file sharing</tag>
  </tags>
  &goffi;
  <revision>
    <version>0.1.1</version>
    <date>2025-10-13</date>
    <initials>jp</initials>
    <remark>
      <ul>
        <li>Replaced XEP-0446 with XEP-0447, which is necessary to have file sources.</li>
        <li>Fixed the incorrectly‑named &lt;file&gt; element (now &lt;file-input&gt;).</li>
        <li>Add tags.</li>
        <li>Various minor fixes.</li>
      </ul>
    </remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1.0</version>
    <date>2025-07-09</date>
    <initials>XEP Editor: dg</initials>
      <remark><p>Accepted as Experimental by Concil vote on 2025-07-08</p>
    </remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2025-06-15</date>
    <initials>jp</initials>
    <remark><p>First draft.</p></remark>
  </revision>
</header>

<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  <p>When using &xep0004;, it can sometimes be useful to let the user upload one or several files. For instance, a ticket system based on &xep0346; may need such a feature. This documentation specifies a "file-input" element which can be used for this.</p>
  <p>This specification differs from &xep0221;: XEP-0221 is used to display media in a form (e.g., for a CAPTCHA), while this specification is a way to upload and share files, for instance to attach them to a ticket system.</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic="Requirements" anchor="reqs">
  <p>The design goals of this XEP are:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>To work with file upload methods such as &xep0234; and &xep0363;</li>
    <li>To allow for one or multiple files upload.</li>
    <li>To add hints for user interface, such as the media types expected.</li>
  </ul>
</section1>

<section1 topic='File Input Element' anchor='file-input'>
  <p>The root element for file is &lt;file-input/&gt;. This element MUST be qualified by the "urn:xmpp:file-input:0" namespace. The &lt;file-input/&gt; element MUST be contained within a &lt;field/&gt; element qualified by the 'jabber:x:data' namespace. The &lt;file-input/&gt; element MAY have the "multiple" attribute, which is a boolean indicating whether multiple files are allowed, and defaulting to "false" &BOOLEANNOTE;</p>
  <p>Hints can be given to indicate which kind of files are accepted, and where they must be uploaded. Two elements are used as direct children of the &lt;file-input/&gt; element: &lt;accept/&gt; and &lt;use/&gt;:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>accept</strong>: accept indicates the media types of accepted files. The media type is indicated with the text content of the element. An asterisk character (<strong>*</strong>) can be used to indicate that all subtypes are accepted (e.g., <em>image/*</em> indicates that any kind of image is accepted). The &lt;accept/&gt; element can be used 0, 1 or any number of times. It is a hint destined to the GUI which will be used with end-users. If no &lt;accept/&gt; element is specified, any file is accepted.</li>
    <li><strong>use</strong>: This element indicates the JID to use for file sharing. This can be useful if a service wants to control the file upload, e.g., to run some workflow on the file upload, such as running a malware check. The client MUST perform a &xep0030; disco#info to discover how to send files to this entity (via &xep0234; or &xep0363;). This element can be used multiple times to indicate which entities can be used, by order of preference. If this element is not present at all, any service can be used (e.g., the user's own server file upload service).</li>
  </ul>
  <p>When submitting the form, the &lt;file-input/&gt; element MAY (and MUST if &lt;required/&gt; is used in the &lt;field/&gt; element) contain one or more &lt;file-sharing/&gt; elements qualified by the "urn:xmpp:sfs:0" namespace as specified by &xep0447;. The already uploaded files SHOULD also be indicated when the form is sent from service to end-user but the service MAY hide already uploaded files if it makes sense for it.</p>
  <section2 topic="examples" anchor="examples">
    <p>In the following example, a form expects a photo to be uploaded. A single file is accepted, and must be an image type.</p>
    <example caption='Inclusion in Data Form'><![CDATA[
    <x xmlns='jabber:x:data' type='form'>
      <!-- … -->
      <field var='photo'>
        <required/>
        <file-input xmlns='urn:xmpp:file-input:0' multiple='false'>
          <accept>image/*</accept>
        </file-input>
      </field>
      <!-- … -->
    </x>
      ]]></example>
    <p>
      In the following example, a form allows multiple file uploads of PDF and LibreOffice text files.
        The &lt;use/&gt; element specifies the upload service, and two files are already uploaded.
    </p>
    <example caption='Form With Already Uploaded Files'><![CDATA[
<x xmlns='jabber:x:data' type='form'>
  <!-- … -->
  <field var='documents'>
    <file-input xmlns='urn:xmpp:file-input:0' multiple='true'>
      <accept>application/pdf</accept>
      <accept>application/vnd.oasis.opendocument.text</accept>
      <use>upload.example.org</use>
      <file-sharing xmlns='urn:xmpp:sfs:0' id="file_1">
        <file xmlns='urn:xmpp:file:metadata:0'>
          <name>balcony_architecture.pdf</name>
          <media-type>application/pdf</media-type>
          <size>123456</size>
          <date>2025-06-15T10:00:00Z</date>
          <hash xmlns='urn:xmpp:hashes:2' algo='sha-256'>aabbccddeeff…</hash>
        </file>
        <sources xmlns='urn:xmpp:sfs:0'>
          <url-data xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/url-data' target='https://upload.example.org/664d1134-64bd-4b83-9a96-25ae52927413/balcony_architecture.pdf' />
        </sources>
      </file-sharing>
      <file-sharing xmlns='urn:xmpp:sfs:0' id="file_2">
        <file xmlns='urn:xmpp:file:metadata:0'>
          <name>serenade.odt</name>
          <media-type>application/vnd.oasis.opendocument.text</media-type>
          <size>789012</size>
          <date>2025-06-15T10:05:00Z</date>
          <hash xmlns='urn:xmpp:hashes:2' algo='sha-256'>112233445566…</hash>
        </file>
        <sources xmlns='urn:xmpp:sfs:0'>
          <url-data xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/url-data' target='https://upload.example.org/30af73ed-d8b5-42f8-87b5-f047dcc7ed85/serenade.odt' />
        </sources>
      </file-sharing>
    </file-input>
  </field>
  <!-- … -->
</x>
]]></example>
  </section2>
</section1>

<section1 topic="Implementation Notes" anchor="impl">
  <p>As it is usual with data forms, the hints can't be enforced. The entity consulting the submitted form SHOULD check the file types, the number of files, the file location, and any other relevant data to see if they match the expected values.</p>
  <p>If a single file is expected to be uploaded (with attribute "multiple" set to "false"), a file has already been uploaded in the form, and a user submits a new file, the service MAY automatically delete the old file to replace it with the new one. This should be clearly indicated to end-users, e.g., via a form note, or via service documentation.</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
  <p>File sharing comes with several security implications; the security considerations of &xep0234;, &xep0363;, and &xep0447; apply here.</p>
  <p>When using a suggested JID to send a file (with the &lt;use/&gt; element), the client IP may be exposed. Clients SHOULD mitigate that with appropriate measures (like warning the user, ignoring the &lt;/use&gt; element, using a proxy, etc).</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
  <p>This document does not require interaction with &IANA;.</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <p>TODO</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic='XML Schema' anchor='schema'>
  <p>TODO</p>
</section1>

</xep>
