<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
<!ENTITY otr3 "<span class='ref'><link url='https://otr.cypherpunks.ca/Protocol-v3-4.0.0.html'>Off-the-Record Messaging Protocol version 3</link></span> <note>Off-the-Record Messaging Protocol (OTR) version 3 &lt;<link url='https://otr.cypherpunks.ca/Protocol-v3-4.0.0.html'>https://otr.cypherpunks.ca/Protocol-v3-4.0.0.html</link>&gt; (Accessed 2015-08-30).</note>" >
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
	<header>
		<title>OTR Discovery</title>
		<abstract>
			This document provides a mechanism by which OTR encryption support can be
			discovered in XMPP, without relying on OTRs protocol agnostic discovery
			mechanism.
		</abstract>
		&LEGALNOTICE;
		<number>0378</number>
		<status>Experimental</status>
		<type>Standards Track</type>
		<sig>Standards</sig>
		<approver>Council</approver>
		<dependencies>
			<spec>XMPP Core</spec>
			<spec>XEP-0030</spec>
		</dependencies>
		<supersedes/>
		<supersededby/>
		<shortname>OTR-DISCO</shortname>
		&sam;
		<revision>
			<version>0.0.1</version>
			<date>2016-07-15</date>
			<initials>ssw</initials>
			<remark><p>Initial version approved by the Council.</p></remark>
		</revision>
	</header>
	<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
		<p>
			The Off-the-Record messaging protocol (OTR) is widely layered on top of
			XMPP to provide end-to-end encryption. Current use of the protocol is
			described in &xep0364;. OTR provides its own discovery mechanism in which
			it sends messages with special whitespace characters to indicate support.
			While this works when initializing a session, there is no way to query a
			client for support and to know in advance that a particular version of
			OTR is supported. This specification aims to solve that by providing an
			in-band mechanism for discovering OTR support in XMPP.
		</p>
		<p>
			It should be noted that newer, more secure encryption protocols exist for
			XMPP, and that new implementations of OTR are discouraged. This protocol
			is primarily intended to solve issues with existing implementations of
			OTR.
		</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='Discovering support' anchor='disco'>
		<p>
      If an entity supports OTR it MUST advertise the fact by returning a
      feature of 'urn:xmpp:otr:0' &VNOTE; in response to a &xep0030; information
      request. This indicates support for OTRv3 as defined by &otr3;.
		</p>
    <example caption='Disco response'><![CDATA[
<feature var='urn:xmpp:otr:0' />]]></example>
		<p>
			If older versions of OTR are required, they may be discovered out of band
			using OTRs built in mechanism which is beyond the scope of this document.
		</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
		<p>
			Because OTR support is advertised outside of any end-to-end encrypted
			stream, it may be subject to downgrade attacks (eg. the server operator
			may remove OTR from the features list).
		</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
		<p>
			This document requires no interaction with the Internet Assigned Numbers
			Authority (IANA).
		</p>
	</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
	<p>This specification defines the following XML namespaces:</p>
	<ul>
		<li>urn:xmpp:otr:0</li>
	</ul>
	<p>
		The &REGISTRAR; shall include the foregoing namespaces in its disco
		features registry as defined in &xep0030;.
	</p>
	<code caption='Registry Submission'><![CDATA[
<var>
	<name>urn:xmpp:otr:0</name>
	<desc>Indicates support for Off-the-Record Messaging (OTR) version 3</desc>
	<doc>XEP-0378</doc>
</var>]]></code>
</section1>
</xep>
