<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE jep SYSTEM '../jep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM '../jep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='../jep.xsl'?>
<jep>
<header>
  <title>Jabber Interest Groups (JIGs)</title>
  <abstract>A definition of Jabber Interest Groups, including their structure and role within the Jabber Software Foundation.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0002</number>
  <status>Active</status>
  <type>Procedural</type>
  <jig>None</jig>
  <approver>Board</approver>
  <dependencies/>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  &stpeter;
  <revision>
    <version>1.1</version>
    <date>2002-01-11</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Clarified some details and added information about cut-offs for inactivity.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <date>2001-06-28</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>First release, modified from Rahul Dave's modification of my original post.</remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Short Definition'>
  <p>A Jabber Interest Group (JIG) is a working group approved by the Jabber Council to address specific areas of growth or concern within the Jabber community, usually by means of developing and publishing Jabber Enhancements Proposals (JEPs).</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Explanation'>
  <p>The main function of most JIGs is to produce acceptable enhancements to the Jabber protocol (delivered in the form of Jabber Enhancement Proposals or JEPs <note>For information about Jabber Enhancement Proposals, see <link url="http://foundation.jabber.org/jeps/jep-0001.html">http://foundation.jabber.org/jeps/jep-0001.html</link>.</note>) within a reasonably limited period of time. However, at the discretion of the Jabber Council, a handful of standing JIGs may be approved (e.g., to address security or standards compliance).</p>
  <p>Anyone (not limited to members of the Jabber Software Foundation) may propose the formation of a JIG by completing a Jabber Enhancement Proposal outlining the need for the JIG and its proposed focus. However, JIG leaders must be members of the Jabber Software Foundation. The number of leaders for a JIG is flexible, and shall be determined by each JIG, in consultation with the Jabber Council if necessary. The concept of "membership" with regard to JIGs is loose, and is essentially co-extensive with membership in the appropriate mailing list (each JIG has its own mailing list, which is archived for public review). JIG members do not need to be members of the Jabber Software Foundation, and any member of the general public may subscribe to JIG mailing lists.</p>
  <p>It is expected that all JIGs (other than certain standing JIGs) will remain active for as long as necessary in order to produce one or more standards-track JEPs for review by the Jabber Council in the JIG's area of focus. However, if a JIG does not show signs of activity for an extended period of time (usually six months of inactivity on the JIG's mailing list), the JIG may be disbanded at the discretion of the Jabber Council with appropriate warning to the JIG members (usually in the form of an email sent to the JIG's mailing list).</p>
</section1>
</jep>
