<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>Jingle</title>
  <abstract>This specification defines an XMPP protocol extension for initiating and managing peer-to-peer media sessions between two XMPP entities in a way that is interoperable with existing Internet standards. The protocol provides a pluggable model that enables the core session management semantics to be used for a wide variety of application types (e.g., voice chat, video chat, file sharing) and with a wide variety of transport methods (e.g., TCP, UDP, ICE, application-specific transports).</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0166</number>
  <status>Experimental</status>
  <type>Standards Track</type>
  <sig>Standards</sig>
  <approver>Council</approver>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>NOT_YET_ASSIGNED</shortname>
  &scottlu;
  &joebeda;
  &stpeter;
  &robmcqueen;
  &seanegan;
  &hildjj;
  <revision>
    <version>0.31</version>
    <date>2008-09-25</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added disposition attribute to content element for mapping to SIP Content-Disposition header.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.30</version>
    <date>2008-09-23</date>
    <initials>ram/psa</initials>
    <remark>
      <ul>
        <li>Allowed content-add in PENDING state.</li>
        <li>Clarified that session-accept action accepts only the content definition(s) in the session-initiate.</li>
        <li>Added optional thread element.</li>
        <li>Clarified tie breaks for transport-replace.</li>
        <li>Modified namespaces to incorporate namespace versioning.</li>
        <li>Cleaned up XML schemas.</li>
      </ul>
    </remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.29</version>
    <date>2008-07-31</date>
    <initials>psa/ram</initials>
    <remark>
      <ul>
        <li>Changed "reliable" vs. "lossy" to "stream" vs. "datagram", since reliability or dependability is orthogonal to the streaming nature of the transport.</li>
        <li>Deleted the "content-remove" action.</li>
        <li>Added "transport-replace" action (answered by "transport-accept").</li>
        <li>Removed &lt;condition/&gt; element as container for Jingle condition elements inside &lt;reason/&gt;, since it introduced an unnecessary layer of indirection.</li>
        <li>Modified state machine to allow content removal during PENDING state.</li>
        <li>Noted that a session can have more than one content instance of the same type.</li>
        <li>Noted that the 'name' attribute is unique to a creator.</li>
        <li>Changed examples to once again use voice chat instead of file transfer.</li>
      </ul>
    </remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.28</version>
    <date>2008-06-16</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Modified state machine to allow content-replace during PENDING state for more seamless handling of fallback scenarios.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.27</version>
    <date>2008-06-04</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Updated examples to track changes to XEP-0167 and retraction of XEP-0180; corrected definition of name attribute to allow semantic meaning.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.26</version>
    <date>2008-05-28</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Corrected several errors in the state diagrams.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.25</version>
    <date>2008-02-29</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>More clearly specified the content-replace action (essentially similar to content-add); specified that content-accept shall be sent in response to content-replace; removed content-modify and content-accept from PENDING state; adjusted text regarding initial session negotiation.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.24</version>
    <date>2008-02-28</date>
    <initials>ram/psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added content-replace action; modified reasoncode and reasontext to use elements instead of attributes; added sid element to handle alternative-session condition; modified examples to use file transfer instead of voice chat; moved profile element to XEP-0167 and XEP-0180.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.23</version>
    <date>2008-01-11</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Removed content-accept after content-remove; removed errors for unsupported-content and unsupported-transports since they are handled via session-terminate; clarified handling of responder attribute.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.22</version>
    <date>2007-12-06</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Modified session flows for busy, unsupported application formats, and unsupported transport methods to enable separation between Jingle core and distinct modules for applications and transports; moved resource determination recommendations to XEP-208.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.21</version>
    <date>2007-11-27</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Further editorial review.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.20</version>
    <date>2007-11-15</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Editorial review and consistency check; moved voice chat scenarios to XEP-0167.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.19</version>
    <date>2007-11-13</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added scenario for handling of busy state, including Jingle-specific error code and modified error flow (no longer an instance of decline).</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.18</version>
    <date>2007-11-08</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added scenarios for various session flows; clarified handling of content-add, content-modify, and content-remove actions; clarified rules for codec priority.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.17</version>
    <date>2007-06-20</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added &lt;unsupported-info/&gt; error.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.16</version>
    <date>2007-06-06</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Clarified resource determination process and updated text to reflect modifications to XEP-0168.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.15</version>
    <date>2007-05-25</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Rewrote introduction and moved historical text to separate section.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.14</version>
    <date>2007-04-17</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Clarified session lifetime; defined reason attribute and associated registry; further specified conformance requirements.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.13</version>
    <date>2007-03-23</date>
    <initials>psa/ram</initials>
    <remark><p>Simplified signalling process and state chart; Removed session-redirect action (use redirect error instead); removed content-decline action; removed transport-* actions (except transport-info for ICE negotiation); removed description-* actions; simplified syntax to allow only one transport per content type; corrected syntax of creator attribute to be either initiator or responder (not JIDs); added profile attribute to content element in order to specify RTP profile in use.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.12</version>
    <date>2006-12-21</date>
    <initials>psa/ram</initials>
    <remark><p>Added creator attribute to content element for prevention of race condition; modified spec to use provisional namespace before advancement to Draft (per XEP-0053).</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.11</version>
    <date>2006-10-31</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Completed clarifications and corrections throughout; added section on Jingle Actions.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.10</version>
    <date>2006-09-29</date>
    <initials>ram/psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Made several corrections to the state machines and examples.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.9</version>
    <date>2006-09-08</date>
    <initials>ram/psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Further cleaned up state machines and state-related actions.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.8</version>
    <date>2006-08-23</date>
    <initials>ram/psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Changed channels to components in line with ICE; changed various action names for consistency; added session-extend and session-reduce actions to add and remove description/transport pairs; added description-modify action; added sender attribute to specify directionality.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.7</version>
    <date>2006-07-17</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added implementation note about handling multiple content types.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.6</version>
    <date>2006-07-12</date>
    <initials>se/psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Changed media type to content type.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.5</version>
    <date>2006-03-20</date>
    <initials>psa/jb</initials>
    <remark><p>Further clarified state machine diagrams; specified that session accept must include agreed-upon media format and transport description; moved deployment notes to appropriate transport spec.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.4</version>
    <date>2006-03-01</date>
    <initials>psa/jb</initials>
    <remark><p>Added glossary; clarified state machines; updated to reflect publication of XEP-0176 and XEP-0177.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.3</version>
    <date>2006-02-24</date>
    <initials>psa/jb</initials>
    <remark><p>Provided more detail about modify scenarios; defined media-specific and transport-specific actions and adjusted state machine accordingly.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.2</version>
    <date>2006-02-13</date>
    <initials>psa/jb</initials>
    <remark><p>Per agreement among the co-authors, moved transport definition to separate specification, simplified state machine, and made other associated changes to the text, examples, and schemas; also harmonized redirect, decline, and terminate processes.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <date>2005-12-15</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Initial version.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.10</version>
    <date>2005-12-11</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>More fully documented burst mode, connectivity checks, error cases, etc.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.9</version>
    <date>2005-12-08</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Restructured document flow; provided example of burst mode.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.8</version>
    <date>2005-12-05</date>
    <initials>psa/sl/jb</initials>
    <remark><p>Distinguished between dribble mode and burst mode, including mode attribute, service discovery features, and implementation notes; provided detailed resource discovery examples; corrected state chart; specified session termination; specified error conditions; specified semantics of informational messages; began to define security considerations; added Joe Beda as co-author.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.7</version>
    <date>2005-11-08</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added more detail to basic session flow; harmonized candidate negotiation process with ICE.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.6</version>
    <date>2005-10-27</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added XMPP Registrar considerations; defined schema; completed slight syntax cleanup.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.5</version>
    <date>2005-10-21</date>
    <initials>psa/sl</initials>
    <remark><p>Separated method description formats from signalling protocol.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.4</version>
    <date>2005-10-19</date>
    <initials>psa/sl</initials>
    <remark><p>Harmonized basic session flow with Google Talk protocol; added Scott Ludwig as co-author.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.3</version>
    <date>2005-10-10</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark><p>Added more detail to basic session flow.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.2</version>
    <date>2005-10-07</date>
    <initials>psa/jjh</initials>
    <remark><p>Protocol cleanup.</p></remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2005-10-06</date>
    <initials>psa/jjh</initials>
    <remark><p>First draft.</p></remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  <p>The purpose of Jingle is to enable one-to-one, peer-to-peer media sessions between XMPP entities, where the negotiation occurs over the XMPP "channel" and the media is exchanged outside the XMPP channel using technologies such as the Real-time Transport Protocol (RTP; &rfc3550;), the User Datagram Protocol (UDP; &rfc0768;), and &ice;.</p>
  <p>One target application for Jingle is simple voice chat (see &xep0167;). We stress the word "simple". The purpose of Jingle is not to build a full-fledged telephony application that supports call waiting, call forwarding, call transfer, hold music, IVR systems, find-me-follow-me functionality, conference calls, and the like. These features are of interest to some user populations, but adding support for them to the core Jingle layer would introduce unnecessary complexity into a technology that is designed for basic multimedia interaction.</p>
  <p>The purpose of Jingle is not to supplant or replace technologies based on Session Initiation Protocol (SIP; &rfc3261;). Because dual-stack XMPP+SIP clients are difficult to build, Jingle was designed as a pure XMPP signalling protocol. However, Jingle is at the same time designed to interwork with SIP so that the millions of deployed XMPP clients can be added onto existing Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP) networks, rather than limiting XMPP users to a separate and distinct network.</p>
  <p>Jingle is designed in a modular way so that developers can easily add support for multimedia session types other than voice chat, such as video chat (see &xep0180;), application sharing, file sharing, collaborative editing, whiteboarding, and torrent broadcasting. The transport methods are also modular, so that Jingle implementations can use any appropriate media transport (including proprietary methods not standardized through the XMPP Standards Foundation).</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='How It Works' anchor='howitworks'>
  <p>This section provides a friendly introduction to Jingle.</p>
  <p>In essence, Jingle enables two XMPP entities (e.g., romeo@montague.lit and juliet@capulet.lit) to set up, manage, and tear down a multimedia session. The negotiation takes place over XMPP, and the media transfer takes place outside of XMPP. The simplest session flow is as follows:</p>
  <code><![CDATA[
Romeo                         Juliet
  |                             |
  |   session-initiate          |
  |---------------------------->|
  |   ack                       |
  |<----------------------------|
  |   session-accept            |
  |<----------------------------|
  |   ack                       |
  |---------------------------->|
  |   MEDIA SESSION             |
  |<===========================>|
  |   session-terminate         |
  |<----------------------------|
  |   ack                       |
  |---------------------------->|
  |                             |
  ]]></code>
  <p>Naturally, more complex scenarios are possible; such scenarios are described in other specifications, such as <cite>XEP-0167</cite> for voice chat.</p>
  <p>The simplest flow might happen as follows. The example is that of a voice chat offer, where the transport method is &xep0176;.</p>
  <example caption="Initiator sends session-initiate"><![CDATA[
<iq from='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    id='jingle1'
    to='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'>
          action='session-initiate'
          initiator='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <content creator='initiator' name='voice'>
      <description xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:apps:rtp:0' media='audio'>
        <payload-type id='96' name='speex' clockrate='16000'/>
        <payload-type id='97' name='speex' clockrate='8000'/>
        <payload-type id='18' name='G729'/>
        <payload-type id='0' name='PCMU' />
        <payload-type id='103' name='L16' clockrate='16000' channels='2'/>
        <payload-type id='98' name='x-ISAC' clockrate='8000'/>
      </description>
      <transport xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:transports:ice-udp:0'/>
    </content>
  </jingle>
</iq>
  ]]></example>
  <p>Upon receiving the session-initiate stanza, the responder determines whether it can proceed with the negotiation. If there is no error, the responder acknowledges the session initiation request.</p>
  <example caption="Responder acknowledges session-initiate"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='jingle1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='result'/>
  ]]></example>
  <p>After successful transport negotiation (not shown here), the responder accepts the session by sending a session-accept action to the initiator.</p>
  <example caption="Responder definitively accepts the session"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='accept1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-accept'
          initiator='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
          responder='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <content creator='initiator' name='voice'>
      <description xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:apps:rtp:0' media='audio'>
        <payload-type id='97' name='speex' clockrate='8000'/>
        <payload-type id='18' name='G729'/>
      </description>
      <transport xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:transports:ice-udp:0'>
        <candidate component='1'
                   foundation='1'
                   generation='0'
                   ip='192.0.2.3'
                   network='1'
                   port='45664'
                   priority='1678246398'
                   protocol='udp'
                   pwd='asd88fgpdd777uzjYhagZg'
                   type='srflx'
                   ufrag='8hhy'/>
      </transport>
    </content>
  </jingle>
</iq>
  ]]></example>
  <p>And the initiator acknowledges session acceptance:</p>
  <example caption="Initiator acknowledges session acceptance"><![CDATA[
<iq from='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    id='accept1'
    to='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    type='result'/>
  ]]></example>
  <p>The initiator and responder would then exchange media using any of the acceptable codecs.</p>
  <p>Eventually, one of the parties (here the responder) will terminate the session.</p>
  <example caption="Responder terminates the session"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    id='term1'
    to='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-terminate'
          initiator='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <reason>
      <no-error/>
      <text>Sorry, gotta go!</text>
    </reason>
  </jingle>
</iq>
  ]]></example>
  <p>The other party then acknowledges termination of the session:</p>
  <example caption="Initiator acknowledges termination"><![CDATA[
<iq from='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    id='term1'
    to='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    type='result'/>
  ]]></example>
</section1>

<section1 topic='Requirements' anchor='reqs'>
  <p>The protocol defined herein is designed to meet the following requirements:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Make it possible to manage a wide variety of peer-to-peer sessions (including but not limited to voice and video) within XMPP.</li>
    <li>When a peer-to-peer connection cannot be negotiated, make it possible to fall back to relayed communications.</li>
    <li>Clearly separate the signalling channel (XMPP) from the data channel.</li>
    <li>Clearly separate the application formats (e.g., audio) from the transport methods (e.g., RTP).</li>
    <li>Make it possible to add, modify, and remove both application types and transport methods in an existing session.</li>
    <li>Make it relatively easy to implement support for the protocol in standard Jabber/XMPP clients.</li>
    <li>Where communication with non-XMPP entities is needed, push as much complexity as possible onto server-side gateways between the XMPP network and the non-XMPP network.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>This document defines the signalling protocol only. Additional documents specify the following:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><p>Various application formats (audio, video, etc.) and, where possible, mapping of those types to the Session Description Protocol (SDP; see &rfc4566;); examples include <cite>Jingle RTP Sessions</cite> and &xep0234;.</p></li>
    <li><p>Various transport methods; examples include <cite>Jingle ICE-UDP Transport</cite> and &xep0177;.</p></li>
    <li><p>Procedures for mapping the Jingle signalling protocol to existing signalling standards such as the IETF's Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and the ITU's H.323 protocol (see &h323;); see for example &xmppsipmedia;.</p></li>
  </ul>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Terminology' anchor='terms'>
  <section2 topic='Glossary' anchor='terms-glossary'>
  <table caption='Glossary'>
    <tr>
      <th>Term</th>
      <th>Definition</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Application Format</td>
      <td>The data format of the content type being established, which formally declares one purpose of the session (e.g., "voice" or "video"). This is the 'what' of the session (i.e., the bits to be transferred), such as the acceptable codecs when establishing a voice conversation. In Jingle XML syntax the application format is the namespace of the &DESCRIPTION; element.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Component</td>
      <td>A numbered stream of data that needs to be transmitted between the endpoints for a given content type in the context of a given session. It is up to the transport to negotiate the details of each component. Depending on the content type, multiple components might be needed (e.g., one to transmit an RTP stream and another to transmit RTCP timing information).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Content Type</td>
      <td>A pair formed by the combination of one application format and one transport method.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Session</td>
      <td>One or more content types negotiated between two entities. It is delimited in time by a session-initiate action and a session-terminate action. During the lifetime of a session, content types can be added or removed. A session consists of at least one content type at a time.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Transport Method</td>
      <td>The method for establishing data stream(s) between entities. Possible transports might include ICE-TCP, Raw UDP, inband data, etc. This is the 'how' of the session. In Jingle XML syntax this is the namespace of the &TRANSPORT; element. The transport method defines how to transfer bits from one host to another. Each transport method must specify whether it is datagram (thus suitable for applications where some packet loss is tolerable) or stream (thus suitable for applications where packet loss is not tolerable).</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Conventions' anchor='terms-conventions'>
    <p>In diagrams, the following conventions are used:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Dashed lines (---) represent Jingle stanzas that are sent via the XMPP signalling channel.</li>
      <li>Double-dashed lines (===) represent media packets that are sent via the media channel, which typically is not an XMPP channel but a direct or mediated channel between the endpoints.</li>
    </ul>
  </section2>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Concepts and Approach' anchor='concepts'>
  <p>Jingle consists of three parts, each with its own syntax and semantics:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Overall session management</li>
    <li>Application types (the "what")</li>
    <li>Transport methods (the "how")</li>
  </ol>
  <p>This document defines the semantics and syntax for overall session management. It also provides pluggable "slots" for application formats and transport methods, which are specified in separate documents.</p>
  <p>At the most basic level, the process for initial negotiation of a Jingle session is as follows (i.e., the actions that can be generated during the PENDING state):</p>
  <ol>
    <li>One user (the "initiator") sends to another user (the "responder") a session initiation request with at least one content definition.</li>
    <li>If the responder wants to proceed, it acknowledges the session initiation request by sending an IQ result.</li>
    <li>The parties attempt to set up data transmission over the designated transport method as defined in the relevant specification.</li>
    <li>Optionally, either party can add or remove content definitions, or change the direction of the media flow.</li>
    <li>Optionally, either party can send session-info actions (to inform the other party that it is attempting transport negotiation, that its device is ringing, etc.).</li>
    <li>As soon as the responder determines that data can flow over the designated transport, it sends to the initiator a session-accept action.</li>
    <li>The parties start sending data over the transport.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>After the initial session negotiation has been completed and the session is in the ACTIVE state, the parties can adjust the session definition by sending the content-modify, content-remove, content-add, and transport-replace actions. In addition, certain transport methods allow continued sending of transport-info actions while in the ACTIVE state. And naturally the parties can send session-info actions at any time.</p>
  <section2 topic='Overall Session Management' anchor='concepts-session'>
    <p>The state machine for overall session management (i.e., the state per Session ID) is as follows:</p>
    <code>
         o
         |
         | session-initiate
         |
         | +------------------------+
         |/                         |
PENDING  o----------------------+   |
         |  | content-accept,   |   |
         |  | content-add,      |   |
         |  | content-modify,   |   |
         |  | content-remove,   |   |
         |  | session-info,     |   |
         |  | transport-accept, |   |
         |  | transport-info,   |   |
         |  | transport-replace |   |
         |  +-------------------+   |
         |                          |
         | session-accept           |
         |                          |
 ACTIVE  o----------------------+   |
         |  | content-accept,   |   |
         |  | content-add,      |   |
         |  | content-modify,   |   |
         |  | content-remove,   |   |
         |  | session-info,     |   |
         |  | transport-accept, |   |
         |  | transport-info,   |   |
         |  | transport-replace |   |
         |  +-------------------+   |
         |                          |
         +--------------------------+
                                    |
                                    | session-terminate
                                    |
                                    o ENDED
    </code>
    <p>As shown, there are three overall session states:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>PENDING</li>
      <li>ACTIVE</li>
      <li>ENDED</li>
    </ol>
    <p>The actions related to management of the overall Jingle session are as follows (detailed definitions are provided in under <link url='#def-action'>Action Attribute</link>).</p>
    <ul>
      <li>content-accept -- Accept a content-add action received from another party.</li>
      <li>content-add -- Add one or more new content definitions to the session.</li>
      <li>content-modify -- Change the directionality of media sending.</li>
      <li>content-remove -- Remove one or more content definitions from the session.</li>
      <li>session-accept -- Definitively accept a session negotiation.</li>
      <li>session-info -- Send session-level information, such as a ringing message.</li>
      <li>session-initiate -- Request negotiation of a new Jingle session.</li>
      <li>session-terminate -- End an existing session.</li>
      <li>transport-accept -- Accept a transport-replace action received from another party.</li>
      <li>transport-info -- Exchange transport candidates.</li>
      <li>transport-replace -- Redefine a transport method.</li>
    </ul>
  </section2>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Session Flow' anchor='session'>
  <p>This section defines the high-level flow of a Jingle session. More detailed descriptions are provided in the specifications for Jingle application formats and transport methods.</p>
  <section2 topic='Resource Determination' anchor='session-resource'>
    <p>In order to initiate a Jingle session, the initiator needs to determine which of the responder's XMPP resources is best for the desired application format. Methods for doing so are out of scope for this specification. However, see the <link url='#support'>Determining Support</link> section of this document (and associated specifications) for relevant information.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Initiation' anchor='protocol-initiate'>
    <p>Once the initiator has discovered which of the responder's XMPP resources is ideal for the desired application format, it sends a session initiation request to the responder. This request is an IQ-set containing a &JINGLE; element qualified by the 'urn:xmpp:jingle:0' namespace &VNOTE;, where the value of the 'action' attribute is "session-initiate" and where the &JINGLE; element contains one or more &CONTENT; elements. Each &CONTENT; element defines a content type to be transferred during the session, and each &CONTENT; element in turn contains one &DESCRIPTION; child element that specifies a desired application format and one &TRANSPORT; child element that specifies a potential transport method. If either party wishes to propose the use of multiple transport methods for the same application format, it MUST include multiple &CONTENT; elements.</p>
    <example caption="Initiator sends session-initiate"><![CDATA[
<iq from='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    id='jingle1'
    to='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'>
          action='session-initiate'
          initiator='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <content creator='initiator' name='voice'>
      <description xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:apps:rtp:0' media='audio'>
        <payload-type id='96' name='speex' clockrate='16000'/>
        <payload-type id='97' name='speex' clockrate='8000'/>
        <payload-type id='18' name='G729'/>
        <payload-type id='0' name='PCMU' />
        <payload-type id='103' name='L16' clockrate='16000' channels='2'/>
        <payload-type id='98' name='x-ISAC' clockrate='8000'/>
      </description>
      <transport xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:transports:ice-udp:0'/>
    </content>
  </jingle>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <p>Note: The syntax and semantics of the &DESCRIPTION; and &TRANSPORT; elements are out of scope for this document, since they are defined in related specifications. The syntax and semantics of the &JINGLE; and &CONTENT; elements are specified in this document under <link url='#def'>Formal Definition</link>.</p>
    <p>Note: In order to expedite session establishment, the initiator MAY send transport candidates (e.g., for negotiation of the ICE transport) immediately after sending the session-initiate action and before receiving acknowledgement from the responder (i.e., the initiator MUST consider the session to be PENDING even before receiving acknowledgement). Given in-order delivery in accordance with &xmppcore;, the responder will receive such transport-info actions after receiving the session-initiate action (if not, it is appropriate for the responder to return &lt;unknown-session/&gt; errors since according to its state machine the session does not exist).</p>
    <example caption="Responder returns unknown-session error"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='jingle1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='error'>
  <error type='cancel'>
    <bad-request xmlns='urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:xmpp-stanzas'/>
    <unknown-session xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:errors:0'/>
  </error>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Responder Response' anchor='protocol-response'>
    <section3 topic='Acknowledgement' anchor='protocol-response-ack'>
      <p>Unless one of the following errors occurs, the responder SHOULD acknowledge receipt of the initiation request.</p>
      <example caption="Responder acknowledges session-initiate"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='jingle1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='result'/>
      ]]></example>
      <p>However, after acknowledging the session initiation request, the responder might subsequently determine that it cannot proceed with negotiation of the session (e.g., because it does not support any of the offered application formats or transport methods, because a human user is busy or unable to accept the session, because a human user wishes to formally decline the session, etc.). In these cases, the responder SHOULD immediately acknowledge the session initiation request but then terminate the session with an appropriate reason as described in the <link url='#session-terminate'>Termination</link> section of this document.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='Errors' anchor='protocol-response-errors'>
      <p>There are several reasons why the responder might immediately return an error instead of acknowledging receipt of the initiation request:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>The initiator is unknown to the responder and the responder does not communicate with unknown entities.</li>
        <li>The responder does not support Jingle.</li>
        <li>The responder wishes to redirect the request to another address.</li>
        <li>The responder does not have sufficient resources to participate in a session.</li>
        <li>The initiation request was malformed.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>If the initiator is unknown to the responder (e.g., via presence subscription as defined in &rfc3921; or stanza session negotiation as defined in &xep0155;) and the responder has a policy of not communicating via Jingle with unknown entities, it MUST return a &unavailable; error.</p>
      <example caption="Initiator is unknown to responder"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='jingle1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='error'>
  <error type='cancel'>
    <service-unavailable xmlns='urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:xmpp-stanzas'/>
  </error>
</iq>
      ]]></example>
      <p>If the responder does not support Jingle, it MUST return a &unavailable; error.</p>
      <example caption="Responder does not support Jingle"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='jingle1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='error'>
  <error type='cancel'>
    <service-unavailable xmlns='urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:xmpp-stanzas'/>
  </error>
</iq>
      ]]></example>
      <p>If the responder wishes to redirect the request to another address, it MUST return a &redirect; error.</p>
      <example caption="Responder redirection"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='jingle1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='error'>
  <error type='cancel'>
    <redirect xmlns='urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:xmpp-stanzas'>
      xmpp:voicemail@capulet.lit
    </redirect>
  </error>
</iq>
      ]]></example>
      <p>If the responder does not have sufficient resources to participate in a session, it MUST return a &constraint; error.</p>
      <example caption="Responder has insufficent resources"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='jingle1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='error'>
  <error type='wait'>
    <resource-constraint xmlns='urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:xmpp-stanzas'/>
  </error>
</iq>
      ]]></example>
      <p>If the initiation request was malformed, the responder MUST return a &badrequest; error.</p>
      <example caption="Initiation request malformed"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='jingle1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='error'>
  <error type='cancel'>
    <bad-request xmlns='urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:xmpp-stanzas'/>
  </error>
</iq>
      ]]></example>
    </section3>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Negotiation' anchor='session-negotiation'>
    <p>In general, negotiation will be necessary before the parties can agree on an acceptable set of application formats and transport methods. There are many potential parameter combinations, as defined in the relevant specifications for various application formats and transport methods.</p>
    <p>The allowable negotiations (including content-level and transport-level negotiations) are as follows:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Exchanging particular transport candidates via the transport-info action.</li>
      <li>Modifying the communication direction for a content type via the content-modify action.</li>
      <li>Changing the definition of a content type via the transport-replace action (typically to fall back to a more suitable transport).</li>
      <li>Adding a content type via the content-add action.</li>
      <li>Removing a content type via the content-remove action.</li>
    </ul>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Acceptance' anchor='session-acceptance'>
    <p>If (after negotiation of transport methods and application formats as well as checking of transport candidates) the responder determines that it will be able to establish a connection, it sends a definitive acceptance to the initiator.</p>
  <example caption="Responder accepts the session"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='accept1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-accept'
          initiator='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
          responder='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <content creator='initiator' name='voice'>
      <description xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:apps:rtp:0' media='audio'>
        <payload-type id='97' name='speex' clockrate='8000'/>
        <payload-type id='18' name='G729'/>
      </description>
      <transport xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:transports:ice-udp:0'>
        <candidate component='1'
                   foundation='1'
                   generation='0'
                   ip='192.0.2.3'
                   network='1'
                   port='45664'
                   priority='1678246398'
                   protocol='udp'
                   pwd='asd88fgpdd777uzjYhagZg'
                   type='srflx'
                   ufrag='8hhy'/>
      </transport>
    </content>
  </jingle>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <p>The initiator then acknowledges the responder's definitive acceptance, after which the parties can exchange media over the negotiated connection.</p>
    <example caption="Initiator acknowledges session acceptance"><![CDATA[
<iq from='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    id='accept1'
    to='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    type='result'/>
    ]]></example>
    <p>If one of the parties cannot find a suitable transport method or candidate, it SHOULD terminate the session as described below.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Modifying an Active Session' anchor='session-modify'>
    <p>Once a session is in the ACTIVE state, it might be modified via a content-add, content-modify, content-remove, or transport-info action. Examples of such modifications are shown in the specifications for various application formats and transport methods.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Termination' anchor='session-terminate'>
    <p>In order to gracefully end the session (which can be done at any point after acknowledging receipt of the initiation request, including immediately thereafter in order to decline the request), either the responder or the initiator MUST send a session-terminate action to the other party.</p>
    <p>The party that terminates the session SHOULD include a &lt;reason/&gt; element that specifies why the session is being terminated. Examples follow.</p>
    <p>One reason for terminating the session is that the terminating party is busy; in this case, the recommended condition is "busy".</p>
    <example caption="Terminating the session (busy)"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    id='term1'
    to='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-terminate'
          initiator='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <reason>
      <busy/>
    </reason>
  </jingle>
</iq>
  ]]></example>
  <p>Another reason for terminating the session is that the terminating party wishes to formally decline the session; in this case, the recommended condition is "decline".</p>
  <example caption="Terminating the session (session formally declined)"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    id='term2'
    to='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-terminate'
          initiator='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <reason>
      <decline/>
    </reason>
  </jingle>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <p>Another reason for terminating the session is that the terminating party already has an existing session with the other party and wishes to use that session rather than initiate a new session; in this case, the recommended condition is "alternative-session" and the terminating party SHOULD include the session ID of the atlernative session in the &lt;sid/&gt; element.</p>
    <example caption="Terminating the session (existing session)"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    id='term3'
    to='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-terminate'
          initiator='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <reason>
      <alternative-session>
        <sid>b84tkkwlmb48kgfb</sid>
      </alternative-session>
    </reason>
  </jingle>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <p>Another reason for terminating the session is that the terminating party does not support any of the offered application formats; in this case, the recommended condition is "unsupported-applications".</p>
    <example caption="Terminating the session (no offered application format supported)"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    id='term4'
    to='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-terminate'
          initiator='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <reason>
      <unsupported-applications/>
    </reason>
  </jingle>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <p>Another reason for terminating the session is that the terminating party does not support any of the offered transport methods; in this case, the recommended condition is "unsupported-transports".</p>
    <example caption="Terminating the session (no offered transport method supported)"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    id='term5'
    to='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-terminate'
          initiator='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <reason>
      <unsupported-transports/>
    </reason>
  </jingle>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <p>Upon receiving an action of "session-terminate", the other party MUST then acknowledge termination of the session:</p>
    <example caption="Acknowledging termination"><![CDATA[
<iq from='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    id='term1'
    to='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    type='result'/>
    ]]></example>
    <p>Note: As soon as an entity sends a session-terminate action, it MUST consider the session to be in the ENDED state (even before receiving acknowledgement from the other party). If the terminating entity receives additional Jingle-related IQ-sets from the other party after sending the session-terminate action, it MUST reply with an &lt;unknown-session/&gt; error.</p>
    <p>Unfortunately, not all sessions end gracefully. In applications of Jingle that also involve the exchange of presence information, receipt of &UNAVAILABLE; from the other party MAY be considered a session-ending event. However, in this case there is nothing for the party to acknowledge.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Informational Messages' anchor='session-info'>
    <p>At any point after initiation of a Jingle session, either entity MAY send an informational message to the other party, for example to inform the other party that a device is ringing.</p>
    <example caption="Responder sends ringing message"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='ringing1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-info'
          initiator='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'>
    <ringing xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:apps:rtp:0:info'/>
  </jingle>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <p>An informational message MUST be an IQ-set containing a &JINGLE; element whose 'action' attribute is set to a value of "session-info" or "transport-info"; the &JINGLE; element SHOULD further contain a payload child element (specific to the application format or transport method) that specifies the information being communicated. If the party that receives an informational message does not understand the payload, it MUST return a &feature; error with a Jingle-specific error condition of &lt;unsupported-info/&gt;.</p>
    <example caption="Responder returns unsupported-info error"><![CDATA[
<iq from='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    id='ringing1'
    to='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    type='error'>
  <error type='modify'>
    <feature-not-implemented xmlns='urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:xmpp-stanzas'/>
    <unsupported-info xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:errors:0'/>
  </error>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <p>However, the &JINGLE; element associated with a session-info action MAY be empty. If either party receives an empty session-info action for an active session, it MUST send an empty IQ result; this usage functions as a "ping" to determine session vitality.</p>
    <example caption="Responder sends session ping"><![CDATA[
<iq from='juliet@capulet.com/balcony'
    id='ping1'
    to='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
    type='set'>
  <jingle xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
          action='session-info'
          initiator='romeo@montague.net/orchard'
          sid='a73sjjvkla37jfea'/>
</iq>
    ]]></example>
    <example caption="Initiator returns IQ-result"><![CDATA[
<iq from='romeo@montague.lit/orchard'
    id='ping1'
    to='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony'
    type='result'/>
    ]]></example>
  </section2>
</section1>

<section1 topic='Formal Definition' anchor='def'>
  <section2 topic='Jingle Element' anchor='def-jingle'>
    <p>The &JINGLE; element MAY be empty or contain one or more &CONTENT; elements (for which see <link url='#def-content'>Content Element</link>).</p>
    <p>The attributes of the &JINGLE; element are as follows.</p>
    <table caption='Attributes of Jingle Element'>
      <tr>
        <th>Attribute</th>
        <th>Definition</th>
        <th>Inclusion</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>action</td>
        <td>A Jingle action as described under <link url='#def-action'>Action Attribute</link>.</td>
        <td>REQUIRED</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>initiator</td>
        <td>The full JID of the entity that has initiated the session flow (which can be different from the 'from' address on the IQ-set).</td>
        <td>REQUIRED</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>responder</td>
        <td>The full JID of the entity that has replied to the initiation, which can be different from the 'to' address on the IQ-set.</td>
        <td>RECOMMENDED</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>sid</td>
        <td>A random session identifier generated by the initiator, which effectively maps to the local-part of a SIP "Call-ID" parameter; this SHOULD match the XML Nmtoken production <note>See &lt;<link url='http://www.w3.org/TR/2000/WD-xml-2e-20000814#NT-Nmtoken'>http://www.w3.org/TR/2000/WD-xml-2e-20000814#NT-Nmtoken</link>&gt;</note> so that XML character escaping is not needed for characters such as '&amp;'.</td>
        <td>REQUIRED</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Action Attribute' anchor='def-action'>
    <p>The value of the 'action' attribute SHOULD be one of the following. If an entity receives a value not defined here, it SHOULD ignore attribute and SHOULD return a &badrequest; error to the sender.</p>
    <section3 topic='content-accept' anchor='def-action-content-accept'>
      <p>The <strong>content-accept</strong> action is used to accept a content-add action received from another party.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='content-add' anchor='def-action-content-add'>
      <p>The <strong>content-add</strong> action is used to add one or more new content definitions to the session. The sender MUST specify only the added content definition(s), not the added content definition(s) plus the existing content definition(s). Therefore it is the responsibility of the recipient to maintain a local copy of the current content definition(s). If the recipient wishes to include the new content definition in the session, it MUST send a content-accept action to the other party.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='content-modify' anchor='def-action-content-modify'>
      <p>The <strong>content-modify</strong> action is used to change the direction of an existing content definition thorugh modification of the 'senders' attribute. If the recipient deems the directionality of a content-modify action to be unacceptable, it MAY reply with a contrary content-modify action, terminate the session, or simply refuse to send or accept application data in the new direction. In any case, the recipient MUST NOT send a content-accept action in response to the content-modify.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='content-remove' anchor='def-action-content-remove'>
      <p>The <strong>content-remove</strong> action is used to remove one or more content definitions from the session. The sender MUST specify only the removed content definition(s), not the removed content definition(s) plus the remaining content definition(s). Therefore it is the responsibility of the recipient to maintain a local copy of the current content definition(s). Upon receiving a content-remove from the other party, the recipient MUST NOT send a content-accept and MUST NOT continue to negotiate the transport method related to that content definition or send application data related to that content definition.  <note>If the content-remove results in zero content definitions for the session, the entity that receives the content-remove SHOULD send a session-terminate action to the other party (since a session with no content definitions is void).</note></p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='session-accept' anchor='def-action-session-accept'>
      <p>The <strong>session-accept</strong> action is used to definitively accept a session negotiation (implicitly this action also serves as a content-accept). A session-accept action indicates acceptance <em>only</em> of the content definition(s) included in the session-initiate, not any content definition(s) subsequently added during the PENDING state. In the session-accept stanza, the &JINGLE; element MUST contain one or more &lt;content/&gt; elements, each of which MUST contain one &lt;description/&gt; element and one &lt;transport/&gt; element. The &JINGLE; element SHOULD possess a 'responder' attribute that explicitly specifies the full JID of the responding entity; after sending acknowledgement of the session-accept, the initiator SHOULD send all future commmunications about this Jingle session to the JID provided in the 'responder' attribute and note the new JID in the user interface.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='session-info' anchor='def-action-session-info'>
      <p>The <strong>session-info</strong> action is used to send session-level information, such as (for Jingle RTP sessions) a ringing message.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='session-initiate' anchor='def-action-session-initiate'>
      <p>The <strong>session-initiate</strong> action is used to request negotiation of a new Jingle session.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='session-terminate' anchor='def-action-session-terminate'>
      <p>The <strong>session-terminate</strong> action is used to end an existing session.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='transport-accept' anchor='def-action-transport-accept'>
      <p>The <strong>transport-accept</strong> action is used to accept a transport-replace action received from another party.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='transport-info' anchor='def-action-transport-info'>
      <p>The <strong>transport-info</strong> action is used to exchange transport candidates; it is mainly used in <cite>XEP-0176</cite> but might be used in other transport specifications.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='transport-replace' anchor='def-action-transport-replace'>
      <p>The <strong>transport-replace</strong> action is used to redefine a transport method.</p>
    </section3>
    <section3 topic='Tie Breaking Related to Jingle Actions' anchor='def-action-ties'>
      <p>It is possible that two instances of certain actions can be sent at the same time in the context of an existing session, one by each party; for example, both parties might simulaneously attempt to send a content-add, content-modify, or content-remove action. In all such cases, the action sent by the initiator MUST overrule the action sent by the responder; i.e., both parties MUST accept the action sent by the initiator and the initiator MUST return an &unexpected; error to the responder for the duplicate action.</p>
    </section3>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Content Element' anchor='def-content'>
    <p>The attributes of the &CONTENT; element are as follows.</p>
    <table caption='Attributes of Content Element'>
      <tr>
        <th>Attribute</th>
        <th>Definition</th>
        <th>Inclusion</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>creator</td>
        <td>Which party originally generated the content type (used to prevent race conditions regarding modifications); the defined values are "initiator" and "responder" (where the default is "initiator").</td>
        <td>REQUIRED</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>disposition</td>
        <td>How the content definition is to be interpreted by the recipient. The meaning of this attribute matches the "Content-Disposition" header as defined in &rfc2183; and applied to SIP by <cite>RFC 3261</cite>. The value of this attribute SHOULD be one of the values registered in the &ianadispositions;. The default value of this attribute is "session".</td>
        <td>OPTIONAL</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>name</td>
        <td>A unique name or identifier for the content type according to the creator, which MAY have meaning to a human user in order to differentiate this content type from other content types (e.g., two content types containing video media could differentiate between "room-pan" and "slides").</td>
        <td>REQUIRED</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>senders</td>
        <td>Which parties in the session will be generating content; the allowable values are "initiator", "responder", or "both" (where the default is "both").</td>
        <td>RECOMMENDED</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Reason Element' anchor='def-reason'>
    <p>The structure of the &lt;reason/&gt; element is as follows.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>The &lt;reason/&gt; element MUST contain an element that provides machine-readable information about the condition that prompted the action.</li>
      <li>The &lt;reason/&gt; element MAY contain a &lt;text/&gt; element that provides human-readable information about the reason for the action.</li>
      <li>The &lt;reason/&gt; element MAY contain an element qualified by some other namespace that provides more detailed machine-readable information about the reason for the action.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>The defined conditions are described in the following table.</p>
    <table caption='Defined Conditions'>
      <tr>
        <th>Element</th>
        <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;alternative-session/&gt;</td>
        <td>The party prefers to use an existing session with the peer rather than initiate a new session; the Jingle session ID of the alternative session SHOULD be provided as the XML character data of the &lt;sid/&gt; child.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;busy/&gt;</td>
        <td>The party is busy and cannot accept a session.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;connectivity-error/&gt;</td>
        <td>The action is related to connectivity problems.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;decline/&gt;</td>
        <td>The party wishes to formally decline the session.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;general-error/&gt;</td>
        <td>The action is related to a non-specific application error.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;media-error/&gt;</td>
        <td>The action is related to media processing problems.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;no-error/&gt;</td>
        <td>The action is generated during the normal course of state management.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;success/&gt;</td>
        <td>The session has been successfully completed.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;unsupported-applications/&gt;</td>
        <td>The party supports none of the offered application types.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&lt;unsupported-transports/&gt;</td>
        <td>The party supports none of the offered transport methods.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Thread Element' anchor='def-thread'>
    <p>The syntax and semantics of the &lt;thread/&gt; element exactly matches that of the &lt;thread/&gt; element as defined for the &MESSAGE; stanza (qualified by the 'jabber:client' namespace) as defined in &xmppim;. It is used to associate a Jingle session or sessions with an ongoing conversation, so that user interfaces with the ability to present multiple interactions in the same window can show an association between the conversation and the Jingle session(s).</p>
  </section2>
</section1>

<section1 topic='Error Handling' anchor='errors'>
  <p>The Jingle-specific error conditions are as follows. These condition elements are qualified by the 'urn:xmpp:jingle:errors:0' namespace &VNOTE;.</p>
  <table caption='Error Conditions'>
    <tr>
      <th>Jingle Condition</th>
      <th>XMPP Condition</th>
      <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;out-of-order/&gt;</td>
      <td>&unexpected;</td>
      <td>The request cannot occur at this point in the state machine (e.g., session-initiate after session-accept).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;unknown-session/&gt;</td>
      <td>&badrequest;</td>
      <td>The 'sid' attribute specifies a session that is unknown to the recipient (e.g., no longer live according to the recipient's state machine because the recipient previously terminated the session).</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>&lt;unsupported-info/&gt;</td>
      <td>&feature;</td>
      <td>The recipient does not support the informational payload of a session-info action.</td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</section1>

<section1 topic='Determining Support' anchor='support'>
  <p>If an entity supports Jingle, it MUST advertise that fact by returning a feature of "urn:xmpp:jingle:0" &VNOTE; in response to a &xep0030; information request. The response MUST also include features for the application formats and transport methods supported by the responding entity, as described in the relevant specifications.</p>
  <example caption="Service Discovery Information Request"><![CDATA[
<iq from='kingclaudius@shakespeare.lit/castle'
    id='disco1'
    to='laertes@shakespeare.lit/castle'
    type='get'>
  <query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'/>
</iq>
  ]]></example>
  <example caption="Service Discovery Information Response"><![CDATA[
<iq from='laertes@shakespeare.lit/castle'
    id='disco1'
    to='kingclaudius@shakespeare.lit/castle'
    type='result'>
  <query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'>
    ...
    <feature var='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'/>
    ...
  </query>
</iq>
  ]]></example>
  <p>In order for an application to determine whether an entity supports this protocol, where possible it SHOULD use the dynamic, presence-based profile of service discovery defined in &xep0115;. However, if an application has not received entity capabilities information from an entity, it SHOULD use explicit service discovery instead.</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic='Conformance by Using Protocols' anchor='conformance'>
  <section2 topic='Application Formats' anchor='conformance-apps'>
    <p>A document that specifies a Jingle application format (e.g., RTP sessions) MUST define:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>How successful application format negotiation occurs.</li>
      <li>A &DESCRIPTION; element and associated semantics for representing the application format.</li>
      <li>If and how the application format can be mapped to the Session Description Protocol, including the appropriate SDP media type (see Section 8.2.1 of <cite>RFC 4566</cite>).</li>
      <li>Whether the media for the application format shall be sent over a stream transport method or a datagram transport method (or, if both, which is preferred).</li>
      <li>Exactly how the media is to be sent and received over a stream or datagram transport.</li>
    </ol>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Transport Methods' anchor='conformance-transports'>
    <p>A document that specifies a Jingle transport method (e.g., raw UDP) MUST define:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>How successful transport negotiation occurs.</li>
      <li>A &TRANSPORT; element and associated semantics for representing the transport method.</li>
      <li>Whether the transport is stream or datagram.</li>
      <li>If and how the transport handles "components" (e.g., for the Real Time Control Protocol).</li>
    </ol>
  </section2>
</section1>

<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
  <section2 topic='Denial of Service' anchor='security-dos'>
    <p>Jingle sessions can be resource-intensive. Therefore, it is possible to launch a denial-of-service attack against an entity by burdening it with too many Jingle sessions. Care must be taken to accept sessions only from known entities and only if the entity's device is able to process such sessions.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Communication Through Gateways' anchor='security-gateways'>
    <p>Jingle communications can be enabled through gateways to non-XMPP networks, whose security characteristics can be quite different from those of XMPP networks. (For example, on some SIP networks authentication is optional and "from" addresses can be easily forged.) Care must be taken in communicating through such gateways.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Information Exposure' anchor='security-info'>
    <p>Mere negotiation of a Jingle session can expose sensitive information about the parties (e.g., IP addresses). Care must be taken in communicating such information, and end-to-end encryption should be used if the parties do not trust the intermediate servers or gateways.</p>
  </section2>
</section1>

<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
  <p>This document requires no interaction with &IANA;.</p>
</section1>

<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <section2 topic='Protocol Namespaces' anchor='registrar-ns'>
    <p>This specification defines the following XML namespaces:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>urn:xmpp:jingle:0</li>
      <li>urn:xmpp:jingle:errors:0</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Upon advancement of this specification from a status of Experimental to a status of Draft, the &REGISTRAR; shall add the foregoing namespaces to the registry located at &NAMESPACES;, as described in Section 4 of &xep0053;.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Namespace Versioning' anchor='registrar-versioning'>
    <p>If the protocol defined in this specification undergoes a major revision that is not fully backward-compatible with an older version, or that contains significant new features, the XMPP Registrar shall increment the protocol version number found at the end of the XML namespaces defined herein, as described in Section 4 of <cite>XEP-0053</cite>.</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Jingle Application Formats Registry' anchor='registrar-apps'>
    <p>The XMPP Registrar shall maintain a registry of Jingle application formats. All application format registrations shall be defined in separate specifications (not in this document). Application types defined within the XEP series MUST be registered with the XMPP Registrar, resulting in protocol URNs of the form "urn:xmpp:jingle:app:name" (where "name" is the registered name of the application format).</p>
    &REGPROCESS;
    <code><![CDATA[
<application>
  <name>The name of the application format.</name>
  <desc>A natural-language summary of the application format.</desc>
  <transport>
    Whether the media can be sent over a "stream" transport, 
    a "datagram" transport, or "both".
  </transport>
  <doc>The document in which the application format is specified.</doc>
</application>
    ]]></code>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Jingle Transport Methods Registry' anchor='registrar-transports'>
    <p>The XMPP Registrar shall maintain a registry of Jingle transport methods. All transport method registrations shall be defined in separate specifications (not in this document). Transport methods defined within the XEP series MUST be registered with the XMPP Registrar, resulting in protocol URNs of the form "urn:xmpp:jingle:transport:name" (where "name" is the registered name of the transport method).</p>
    &REGPROCESS;
    <code><![CDATA[
<transport>
  <name>the name of the transport method</name>
  <desc>a natural-language summary of the transport method</desc>
  <type>whether the transport method can be "stream", "datagram", or "both"</type>
  <doc>the document in which this transport method is specified</doc>
</transport>
    ]]></code>
  </section2>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XML Schemas' anchor='schema'>
  <section2 topic='Jingle' anchor='schema-jingle'>
    <code><![CDATA[
<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<xs:schema
    xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema'
    targetNamespace='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
    xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:0'
    elementFormDefault='qualified'>

  <xs:element name='jingle'>
    <xs:complexType>
      <xs:sequence>
        <xs:element ref='content' 
                    type='contentElementType'
                    minOccurs='0' 
                    maxOccurs='unbounded'/>
        <xs:element ref='reason' 
                    type='reasonElementType'
                    minOccurs='0' 
                    maxOccurs='1'/>
        <xs:element ref='thread' 
                    type='threadElementType'
                    minOccurs='0' 
                    maxOccurs='1'/>
        <xs:any namespace='##other' minOccurs='0' maxOccurs='unbounded'/>
      </xs:sequence>
      <xs:attribute name='action' use='required'>
        <xs:simpleType>
          <xs:restriction base='xs:NCName'>
            <xs:enumeration value='content-accept'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='content-add'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='content-modify'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='content-remove'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='session-accept'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='session-info'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='session-initiate'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='session-terminate'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='transport-add'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='transport-info'/>
            <xs:enumeration value='transport-replace'/>
          </xs:restriction>
        </xs:simpleType>
      </xs:attribute>
      <xs:attribute name='initiator' type='xs:string' use='required'/>
      <xs:attribute name='responder' type='xs:string' use='optional'/>
      <xs:attribute name='sid' type='xs:NMTOKEN' use='required'/>
    </xs:complexType>
  </xs:element>

  <xs:complexType name='alternativeSessionElementType'>
    <xs:sequence>
      <xs:element name='sid'
                  minOccurs='0'
                  maxOcccurs='1'
                  type='xs:NMTOKEN'/>
    </xs:sequence>
  </xs:complexType>

  <xs:complexType name='contentElementType'>
    <xs:sequence>
      <xs:any namespace='##other' minOccurs='0' maxOccurs='unbounded'/>
    </xs:sequence>
    <xs:attribute name='creator'
                  use='required'
                  default='initiator'>
      <xs:simpleType>
        <xs:restriction base='xs:NCName'>
          <xs:enumeration value='initiator'>
          <xs:enumeration value='responder'/>
        </xs:restriction>
      </xs:simpleType>
    </xs:attribute>
    <xs:attribute name='disposition'
                  use='optional'
                  type='xs:NCName'
                  default='session'/>
    <xs:attribute name='name'
                  use='required'
                  type='xs:string'/>
    <xs:attribute name='senders'
                  use='optional'
                  default='both'>
      <xs:simpleType>
        <xs:restriction base='xs:NCName'>
          <xs:enumeration value='both'>
          <xs:enumeration value='initiator'>
          <xs:enumeration value='responder'/>
        </xs:restriction>
      </xs:simpleType>
    </xs:attribute>
  </xs:complexType>

  <xs:complexType name='reasonElementType'>
    <xs:sequence>
      <xs:choice>
        <xs:element name='alternative-session' 
                    type='alternativeSessionElementType'/>
        <xs:element name='busy' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='connectivity-error' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='decline' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='general-error' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='invalid-credentials' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='media-error' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='no-error' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='success' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='unsupported-applications' type='empty'/>
        <xs:element name='unsupported-transports' type='empty'/>
      </xs:choice>
      <xs:element name='text' type='xs:string' minOccurs='0' maxOccurs='1'/>
      <xs:any namespace='##other' minOccurs='0' maxOccurs='1'/>
    </xs:sequence>
  </xs:complexType>

  <xs:complexType name='threadElementType'>
    <xs:simpleContent>
      <xs:extension base='xs:NMTOKEN'>
        <xs:attribute name='parent'
                      type='xs:NMTOKEN'
                      use='optional'/>
      </xs:extension>
    </xs:simpleContent>
  </xs:complexType>

  <xs:simpleType name='empty'>
    <xs:restriction base='xs:string'>
      <xs:enumeration value=''/>
    </xs:restriction>
  </xs:simpleType>

</xs:schema>
    ]]></code>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Jingle Errors' anchor='schema-errors'>
    <code><![CDATA[
<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<xs:schema
    xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema'
    targetNamespace='urn:xmpp:jingle:errors:0'
    xmlns='urn:xmpp:jingle:errors:0'
    elementFormDefault='qualified'>

  <xs:element name='out-of-order' type='empty'/>
  <xs:element name='unknown-session' type='empty'/>
  <xs:element name='unsupported-info' type='empty'/>

  <xs:simpleType name='empty'>
    <xs:restriction base='xs:string'>
      <xs:enumeration value=''/>
    </xs:restriction>
  </xs:simpleType>

</xs:schema>
    ]]></code>
  </section2>
</section1>

<section1 topic='History' anchor='history'>
  <p>Until Jingle was developed, there existed no widely-adopted standard for initiating and managing peer-to-peer interactions between XMPP entities. Although several large service providers and Jabber client teams had written and implemented their own proprietary XMPP extensions for peer-to-peer signalling (usually only for voice), those technologies were not open and did not always take into account requirements to interoperate with SIP-based technologies. The only existing open protocol was &xep0111;, which made it possible to initiate and manage peer-to-peer sessions, but which did not provide enough of the key signalling semantics to be easily implemented in Jabber/XMPP clients. <note>It is true that TINS made it relatively easy to implement an XMPP-to-SIP gateway; however, in line with the long-time Jabber philosophy of "simple clients, complex servers", it would be better to force complexity onto the server-side gateway and to keep the client as simple as possible.</note></p>
  <p>The result was an unfortunate fragmentation within the XMPP community regarding signalling protocols. Essentially, there were two possible approaches to solving the problem:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Recommend that all client developers implement a dual-stack (XMPP + SIP) solution.</li>
    <li>Define a full-featured protocol for XMPP signalling.</li>
  </ol>
  <p>Implementation experience indicates that a dual-stack approach might not be feasible on all the computing platforms for which Jabber clients have been written, or even desirable on platforms where it is feasible. <note>For example, one large ISP decided to switch to a pure XMPP approach after having implemented and deployed a dual-stack client for several years.</note> Therefore, it seemed reasonable to define an XMPP signalling protocol that could provide the necessary session management semantics while also making it relatively straightforward to interoperate with existing Internet standards.</p>
  <p>As a result of feedback received on <cite>XEP-0111</cite>, the original authors of this document (Joe Hildebrand and Peter Saint-Andre) began to define such a signalling protocol, code-named Jingle. Upon communication with members of the Google Talk team, <note>Google Talk is a messaging and voice chat service and client provided by Google; see &lt;<link url='http://www.google.com/talk/'>http://www.google.com/talk/</link>&gt;.</note> it was discovered that the emerging Jingle approach was conceptually (and even syntactically) quite similar to the signalling protocol used in the Google Talk application. Therefore, in the interest of interoperability and adoption, we decided to harmonize the two approaches. The signalling protocol specified herein is, therefore, substantially equivalent to the original Google Talk protocol, with several adjustments based on feedback received from implementors as well as for publication by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Acknowledgements' anchor='ack'>
  <p>The authors would like to thank Rohan Mahy for his valuable input on early versions of the Jingle specifications. Thiago Camargo, Diana Cionoiu, Olivier Cr&#234;te, Dafydd Harries, Antti Ij&#228;s, Tim Julien, Lauri Kaila, Justin Karneges, Jussi Laako, Steffen Larsen, Anthony Minessale, Akito Nozaki, Matt O'Gorman, Rob Taylor, Matt Tucker, Justin Uberti, Saku Vainio, Brian West, Jeff Williams, and others have also provided helpful input. Thanks also to those who have commented on the &SSIG; and Jingle <note>Before this specification was formally accepted by the XMPP Standards Foundation as an XMPP Extension Protocol, it was discussed on the semi-private &lt;jingle@jabber.org&gt; mailing list. This list has since been resurrected as a special-purpose venue for discussion of Jingle protocols and implementation; interested developers can subscribe and access the archives at at &lt;<link url='http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/jingle/'>http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/jingle/</link>&gt;.</note> mailing lists.</p>
</section1>
</xep>
