<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE jep SYSTEM '../jep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM '../jep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='../jep.xsl'?>
<jep>
<header>
  <title>Jabber Registrar</title>
  <abstract>This JEP defines the roles and processes of the Jabber Registrar within the Jabber Software Foundation.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>0053</number>
  <status>Active</status>
  <type>Procedural</type>
  <jig>None</jig>
  <approver>Board</approver>
  <dependencies/>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>N/A</shortname>
  &stpeter;
  <revision>
    <version>1.1</version>
    <date>2004-05-20</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Updated to reflect experience.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <date>2003-03-20</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Per a vote of the Jabber Council, advanced status to Active.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.5</version>
    <date>2003-01-21</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Changed name to Jabber Registrar in response to feedback from the JSF Board of Directors.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.4</version>
    <date>2003-01-20</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Added reference to jana@jabber.org mailing list.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.3</version>
    <date>2002-11-22</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Simplified to reflect discussion in the Jabber Council; in particular, reserved JANA functions to the JEP Editor until there is a perceived need for a more formal governing body.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.2</version>
    <date>2002-10-27</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Clarified JANA composition, panel member requirements, and JANA process.</remark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <date>2002-10-24</date>
    <initials>psa</initials>
    <remark>Initial version.</remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction and Purpose'>
  <p>As the &JSF; publishes more protocol specifications (see &jep0001;), it becomes necessary to keep better track of the namespaces defined by those specifications as well as the parameters used in the context of the relevant protocols. (Examples of such parameters include the features and options used in &jep0020; and the identities and features used in &jep0030;.) In particular, the common use of protocols published by the JSF requires that namespaces and particular parameter values be assigned uniquely. It is the role of the Jabber Registrar to make those unique assignments and to maintain registries of the currently assigned values. The Jabber Registrar shall also function as a single point of contact between the Jabber community and &IANA;.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Composition'>
  <p>Until there is a perceived need for a more formal governing body, the functions of the Jabber Registrar shall be managed by the &EDITOR;. In the future, the &COUNCIL; and/or the &BOARD; may decide to create a more formal panel to oversee the functions of the Jabber Registrar; if they do, this JEP shall be updated to reflect the change.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Process'>
  <p>Every Jabber Enhancement Proposal (JEP) must contain a section devoted to "Jabber Registrar Considerations", detailing the namespaces and parameters to be registered with the Jabber Registrar, as well as any new registries to be created as a result of the JEP.</p>
  <p>The registry additions or creations specified in a JEP shall not take effect until the JEP advances to a status of Draft (Standards-Track JEPs) or Active (Informational and Historical JEPs). Registration of namespaces shall be initiated by the JEP Editor when a JEP advances to Draft or Active and shall not require the involvement of the JEP author. Registration of particular parameters used within a specification shall be initiated by the JEP Editor if specified in the JEP, and may also be initiated by implementers of the JEP after it has advanced to Active, Draft, or Final. Creation of new registries shall be initiated by the Jabber Registrar; if a JEP specifies the creation of a new registry, the JEP author is strongly encouraged to consult with the Jabber Registrar before seeking a Last Call on the JEP.</p>
  <p>Requests for namespace and parameter assignments must be sent to the Jabber Registrar in accordance with the process specified in the document (usually a JEP) that defines the relevant registry, normally by sending an appropriately formatted email message to &lt;registrar@jabber.org&gt;. If, in the Registrar's judgment, discussion of a request is required, the Registrar shall initiate such discussion within the &SJIG;. The Registrar shall add registry items at his discretion based on discussion within the Standards JIG if necessary, but shall not unduly restrict registration of parameter values. If a JEP author or implementer thinks that a request was unfairly denied by the Registrar, an appeal of the decision may be directed to the Jabber Council.</p>
  <p>The Jabber Registrar shall maintain registries of assigned namespaces and parameters at &lt;<link url="http://www.jabber.org/registrar/">http://www.jabber.org/registrar/</link>&gt; and shall update those registries in a timely fashion. Changes to JSF registries shall be announced on the Standards-JIG mailing list.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Security Considerations'>
  <p>Security considerations are primarily the responsibility of the protocols in which specific parameters are used. The Jabber Registrar shall respect the security considerations defined in JSF protocol specifications, and shall endeavor to ensure that registered parameter values do not compromise privacy or security in any way.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='IANA Considerations'>
  <p>The Jabber Registrar shall be responsible for interacting with the IANA on behalf of the Jabber community. If a JEP requires interaction with the IANA, that fact shall be noted by the JEP author in the JEP and discussed on the Standards-JIG mailing list along with normal discussion of the JEP. The Jabber Registrar shall collaborate with the JEP author to present an appropriate request to the IANA.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Jabber Registrar Considerations'>
  <p>This entire document defines the processes and procedures of the Jabber Registrar.</p>
</section1>
</jep>
