<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
	<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
	<header>
		<title>Form of Membership Applications</title>
		<abstract>
			This specification outlines the form and mandatory content
			of membership applications.
		</abstract>
		&LEGALNOTICE;
		<number>0345</number>
		<status>Deferred</status>
		<type>Procedural</type>
		<sig>None</sig>
		<approver>Board</approver>
		<dependencies/>
		<supersedes/>
		<supersededby/>
		<shortname>N/A</shortname>
		&dcridland;
  <revision>
    <version>0.4</version>
    <date>2017-09-11</date>
    <initials>XEP Editor (jwi)</initials>
    <remark>Defer due to lack of activity.</remark>
  </revision>
		<revision>
			<version>0.3</version>
			<date>2014-08-04</date>
			<initials>dwd</initials>
			<remark><p>Address Last Call comments</p><p>Add changing applications after voting started.</p></remark>
		</revision>
		<revision>
			<version>0.2</version>
			<date>2014-07-02</date>
			<initials>dwd</initials>
			<remark><p>Remove corporate membership</p></remark>
		</revision>
		<revision>
			<version>0.1</version>
			<date>2014-03-19</date>
			<initials>editor (mam)</initials>
			<remark><p>Initial published version approved by XSF Board of Directors.</p></remark>
		</revision>
		<revision>
			<version>0.0.2</version>
			<date>2014-02-26</date>
			<initials>dwd</initials>
			<remark><p>Fixed typos, added entities and mandatory sections.</p></remark>
		</revision>
		<revision>
			<version>0.0.1</version>
			<date>2013-12-13</date>
			<initials>dwd</initials>
			<remark><p>Initial Version</p></remark>
		</revision>
	</header>
	<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
		<p>Prior to this specification, membership applications have been relatively informal,
		and guidance has been similarly ad-hoc. This document provides the form of membership
		applications, which is part of the remit of the XSF Board.</p>
		<p>The intent is to provide as few rules as possible, but ensure that the XSF has the
		essential information required to make a decision on the application.</p>
		<p>Although this specification provides only a very few mandatory items, most applications include considerably more than this, and the existing members - who will be voting on an application - will be expecting to see sections explaining why someone is applying, and giving a more useful background to the individual. Reviewing past applications is highly recommended, though novel applications - as long as they conform to these minimal requirements - are also welcomed.</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='Who May Apply' anchor='who'>
		<p>This section is not normative; for the strict answer to this question the reader is requested to read the &BYLAWS;.</p>
		<p>At the time of writing, only "natural persons" - that is, ordinary people as opposed to corporations and similar entities regarded as persons in some cases - may apply to join the XMPP Standards Foundation as members. People applying for membership are, in this document, called by the term "Applicants".</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='Where Applications Are Submitted' anchor='submission'>
		<p>Applications are to be submitted as a new Wiki Page on the XSF Wiki,
		and linked from a single Wiki page which will be included in the
		announcement email sent by the XSF Secretary.</p>
		<p>Applicants are solely responsible for their own applications, and the applications shall be their own. Members and prospective members should not edit anyone else's application. Exceptions to this latter shall
		be made only with permission of the Board, the XSF Secretary, or the Executive Director; and
		the Applicant concerned.</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='Challenges and Final Arbiter' anchor='arbiter'>
		<p>In the case that a particular application is questionable for some reason - if it is thought to be missing mandatory information, containing incorrect information, or failing to disclose affiliations - a member may raise a Challenge with the membership, by sending a message to the members list detailing the issues. A member may request a member of the &BOARD; to raise the Challenge anonymously on their behalf; the member of the Board however is in no way compelled to do so.</p>
		<p>The XSF Board is the final arbiter of such Challenges, and shall make a final decision on whether the application should be rejected; however the Board is expected to take into account any rough consensus of the members. Any rejection will include any remedies possible.</p>
		<p>Notwithstanding the final nature of the XSF Board's decision, any application so rejected may be resubmitted by the Applicant, presumably after addressing the issues.</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic="Changes to Applications" anchor='ch-ch-ch-ch-changes'>
		<p>Sometimes the content of an application becomes, or is found to be, incorrect, requiring a change to the application. This may be due to error, a change in circumstances, or for any other reason.</p>
		<p>In some cases, such a change may result in members wishing to change their vote, and in others it may invalidate their application.</p>
		<section2 topic='Before Voting'>
		<p>In the case that voting (including proxy voting) has not yet begun, pages may be changed by the applicant at any time. The application need not notify members or the secretary.</p>
		</section2>
		<section2 topic='During Voting'>
		<p>If voting (including proxy voting) has begun, the applicant must notify the XSF Secretary. Applicants who are existing members should also notify the membership directly themselves. If An Application does not (or if they are not a member), the XSF Secretary shall do so.</p>
		</section2>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='Mandatory Information' anchor='mandatory'>
		<p>The purpose of the mandatory information is to allow the XSF Secretary sufficient information to adhere to the XSF Bylaws. As a secondary purpose, it also allows the XSF members to make an informed decision when voting to accept applications; it is important for Applicants to understand that this mandatory information is unlikely to be sufficient to convince the members, however.</p>
			<p>Applicants must provide:</p>
			<dl>
				<di><dt>Contact Email</dt><dd>A valid email address, specific to the Applicant, suitable for members to contact and request further information.</dd></di>
				<di><dt>Contact Jid</dt><dd>A valid jid, specific to the Applicant, suitable for members to contact and request further information.</dd></di>
				<di><dt>Relevant Affiliations</dt><dd>Any affiliations, as described within the final clause of the XSF Bylaws, Section 2.1. Note that this is not limited to employment, but must include it. Other relevant affiliations include any other organization the applicant may represent.</dd></di>
				<di><dt>Legal Name</dt><dd>A full name by which the Applicant is known and identified for legal purposes. This could be the name on a Natural Applicant's passport.</dd></di>
			</dl>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
		<p>There are privacy implications inherent in the public disclosure of the information in an Application, particularly by a Natural Applicant.</p>
		<p>These are an unavoidable consequence of the Application.</p>
		<p>Applicants may deliberately mislead Members through their applications. This document provides no rememdy for such action., and members are advised to be aware of this possibility.</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
		<p>This document has no considerations for IANA.</p>
	</section1>
	<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
		<p>This document has no considerations for the XMPP Registrar.</p>
	</section1>
</xep>
