<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>MUC Activity Indicator</title>
  <abstract>This specification provides querying entities an approximate indication of the level of activity in a given XEP-0045 Multi-User Chat room.</abstract>
  &LEGALNOTICE;
  <number>xxxx</number>
  <status>ProtoXEP</status>
  <type>Standards Track</type>
  <sig>Standards</sig>
  <approver>Council</approver>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XEP-0030</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0045</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0128</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>NOT_YET_ASSIGNED</shortname>
  <tags/>
  &jonaswielicki;
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2024-11-29</date>
    <initials>jsc</initials>
    <remark><p>Initial submission.</p></remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  <p>Currently, the only activity metric available to entities considering
    interacting with a &xep0045; chat is the number of occupants which is
    published in the &xep0030; response.</p>
  <p>However, the number of occupants alone is not a great metric for
    usefulness of a chat. On the one end of the spectrum there may be highly
    active, but small, groups of experts on a specific topic who are happy to
    help. On the other end of the spectrum there may be huge chats consisting
    mostly of lurkers.</p>
  <p>This specification introduces a new field in the disco#info data which
    gives an indication of the rate at which messages are sent in a given
    group chat.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Requirements' anchor='reqs'>
  <ul>
    <li>MUST NOT impose excessive computing requirements on servers.</li>
    <li>MUST be useful as rough indicator.</li>
  </ul>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Use Cases' anchor='usecases'>
  <section2 topic='Retrieving the message activity level' anchor='retrieve'>
    <p>To request the current level of message activity, an entity sends a standard &xep0030; information request to a MUC's address:</p>
    <example caption='Entity Queries Chat Room for Information'><![CDATA[
<iq from='hag66@shakespeare.lit/pda'
    id='lx09df27'
    to='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit'
    type='get'>
  <query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'/>
</iq>
]]></example>
    <p>Services implementing this specification MUST return the {urn:xmpp:muc-activity}message-activity field, if:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>The room is persistent, and</li>
      <li>The room is public, and</li>
      <li>The data is currently available.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>The field MUST contain an approximation of the number of messages sent per hour in this room as floating point value. For example approximation approaches, see the <link url="#impl">Implementation Notes</link> below.</p>
    <example caption='Service Returns Disco Info Result for Room'><![CDATA[
<iq from='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit'
    id='lx09df27'
    to='hag66@shakespeare.lit/pda'
    type='result'>
  <query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'>
    <!-- ... -->
    <x xmlns='jabber:x:data' type='result'>
      <field var='FORM_TYPE' type='hidden'>
        <value>http://jabber.org/protocol/muc#roominfo</value>
      </field>
      <!-- ... -->
      <field var='{urn:xmpp:muc-activity}message-activity'
             label='Messages per hour'>
        <value>23.42</value>
      </field>
    </x>
  </query>
</iq>
]]></example>
    <p>In particular, services MUST omit the field entirely if the above preconditions are not met. Services MUST NOT put placeholder values in the field.</p>
  </section2>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Business Rules' anchor='rules'>
  <ul>
    <li>The value provided in the form field MUST be in units of messages per hour.</li>
    <li>The time frame over which this number is derived is service-defined. However, services SHOULD NOT take into account messages which are older than 72 hours.</li>
    <li>Services MUST NOT count messages without a &lt;body/&gt; element, unless it is known that this message would be rendered as standalone message on a compliant client nontheless.</li>
    <li>Services MUST NOT count messages where the type is not groupchat; in particular, they MUST NOT count private messages among occupants.</li>
    <li>Services SHOULD NOT count &xep0308; messages.</li>
    <li>Consumers MUST NOT assume that the number is exact.</li>
    <li>Consumers MUST NOT assume that the number is updated in real-time.</li>
    <li>Services SHOULD update the number at least once per hour.</li>
  </ul>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Implementation Notes' anchor='impl'>
  <p>The obvious "correct" implemetation to provide the message rate would be
    to, internally, query the number of messages sent in the room since its
    inception and divide that by the number of hours since its inception.
    Such an implementation is likely to be expensive, in particular for large,
    high-traffic rooms.</p>
  <p>In order to cater for that, the <link url='#rules'>Business Rules</link>
    allow for some significant leeway in how implementations approximate the
    number of messages per hour.</p>
  <p>For implementations where fetching the number of messages in a certain
    time frame is too expensive, the following simplified approach is
    outlined: For each MUC, allocate a shift register of 25 counters. Whenever
    an eligible message is broadcast through the MUC, increase the first
    counter. Every hour, shift the counters onward (so that the first counter
    becomes the second and so on) and reset the first counter to zero. Whenever
    the message rate is requested (via disco#info or otherwise), sum the
    counters two through 25 and divide the sum by 24.</p>
  <p>That way, only constant storage per MUC and constant CPU time per message
    and request is required. As a trade-off, this introduces a latency of one
    hour for updating the counter.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Accessibility Considerations' anchor='access'>
  <p>This specification does not introduce new user interaction concepts.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Internationalization Considerations' anchor='i18n'>
  <p>Services MAY translate the label attribute of the field according to
    the language indicated in the requester's IQ stanza.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
  <p>Services MUST choose a sufficiently cheap algorithm to provide the
    message activity indicator. Otherwise, they are open to trivial
    denial-of-service attacks by high-rate disco#info requests.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Privacy Considerations' anchor='privacy'>
  <p>Services MUST NOT publish message activity indicators for MUCs which are
    not publicly listed (muc_public feature flag) or where users
    would need some kind of specific authorization to join (such as a password
    or the member affiliation).</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
  <p>No IANA interactions required.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <p>The form field should be registered, eventually.</p>
</section1>
</xep>
