<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
  <header>
    <title>Total Conversation Profile</title>
    <abstract>This specification defines a profile for XMPP clients that present audio, video, real-time text, captions, files and optional call-scoped context as one Total Conversation experience.</abstract>
    &LEGALNOTICE;
    <number>xxxx</number>
    <status>ProtoXEP</status>
    <type>Standards Track</type>
    <sig>Standards</sig>
    <approver>Council</approver>
    <dependencies>
      <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0030</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0080</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0166</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0167</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0176</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0215</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0301</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0313</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0343</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0353</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0363</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0479</spec>
    </dependencies>
    <supersedes/>
    <supersededby/>
    <shortname>total-conversation-profile</shortname>
    <tags>
      <tag>accessibility</tag>
      <tag>jingle</tag>
      <tag>rtt</tag>
      <tag>webrtc</tag>
      <tag>profile</tag>
    </tags>
    <author>
      <firstname>Edward</firstname>
      <surname>Tie</surname>
      <email>info@tiedragon.com</email>
    </author>
    <revision>
      <version>0.0.1</version>
      <date>2026-06-15</date>
      <initials>et</initials>
      <remark><p>Initial ProtoXEP submission.</p></remark>
    </revision>
  </header>

  <section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
    <p>Total Conversation is a user experience where real-time text, audio and video are available together as one conversation. XMPP already contains many of the necessary building blocks: &xep0301; for real-time text, &xep0166; and &xep0167; for Jingle calls, &xep0176; and &xep0215; for connectivity, and &xep0313; for archive retrieval.</p>
    <p>However, an implementation can support several of these pieces and still fail to provide a coherent Total Conversation. The user may see audio and video in one call surface, while real-time text is sent as unrelated chat messages. Captions may be indistinguishable from typed text. Location may be global presence instead of call-scoped consent. Archives may not show whether text was synchronized with the call or merely a fallback.</p>
    <p>This specification defines a profile claim and conformance model for XMPP Total Conversation clients. It composes existing XMPP RFCs and XEPs and references Jingle extensions for synchronized real-time text and call-scoped location.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Requirements' anchor='reqs'>
    <p>This specification is designed to meet the following requirements.</p>
    <ol>
      <li>Define what a client means when it claims Total Conversation support.</li>
      <li>Keep normal XMPP messaging, real-time text and Jingle calls interoperable with existing XEPs.</li>
      <li>Define progressive conformance levels from ordinary chat to synchronized Total Conversation.</li>
      <li>Make fallback paths visible to users and assistive technologies.</li>
      <li>Allow clients to discover supported modalities without inventing a new account or media system.</li>
      <li>Describe how archives preserve the difference between synchronized text and fallback text.</li>
      <li>Support accessibility, relay, interpreter, captioning and emergency-readiness experiments without claiming to be an emergency-services standard.</li>
    </ol>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Glossary' anchor='glossary'>
    <dl>
      <di>
        <dt>Total Conversation</dt>
        <dd>A conversation containing simultaneous audio, video and real-time text.</dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>Synchronized text</dt>
        <dd>Real-time text, captions, translation or interpreter text bound to the same Jingle session as audio or video.</dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>Fallback text</dt>
        <dd>Real-time text sent outside the Jingle session, for example using &xep0301; in normal message stanzas.</dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>Assistive context</dt>
        <dd>Conversation metadata such as caption source, call-scoped location, interpreter state, language, fallback state and consent state.</dd>
      </di>
    </dl>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Relationship to Existing XEPs' anchor='relationship'>
    <p>This specification does not replace audio, video, message, archive, file-transfer or encryption specifications. It defines how those specifications fit together when the user-visible product claims Total Conversation support.</p>
    <table caption='Important building blocks'>
      <tr>
        <th>Protocol</th>
        <th>Role in this profile</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&xep0301;</td>
        <td>Live text and fallback RTT outside Jingle.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&xep0166; and &xep0167;</td>
        <td>Jingle signalling and RTP audio/video descriptions.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&xep0176;, &xep0215; and &xep0343;</td>
        <td>Connectivity and WebRTC data channel signalling where applicable.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&xep0353;</td>
        <td>Message-based Jingle proposal and ringing flow.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&xep0313;</td>
        <td>Archive retrieval for messages, metadata and call-history events.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&xep0363; and &xep0447;</td>
        <td>File upload and file metadata for attachments, voice messages, video messages or optional recordings.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>&xep0479;</td>
        <td>General XMPP client compliance baseline.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <p>A client MUST NOT claim this profile as a replacement for the underlying protocol support. For example, advertising the profile without supporting Jingle does not imply audio/video calling.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Conformance Levels' anchor='levels'>
    <p>The profile defines progressive levels. A client MUST NOT advertise a level higher than it can negotiate and present to the user.</p>
    <table caption='Total Conversation levels'>
      <tr>
        <th>Level</th>
        <th>Name</th>
        <th>Required behavior</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>tc-0</td>
        <td>Core conversation</td>
        <td>Authenticated XMPP messaging, presence and service discovery.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>tc-1</td>
        <td>Live text conversation</td>
        <td>tc-0 plus &xep0301; real-time text and readable message body fallback.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>tc-2</td>
        <td>Audio/video conversation</td>
        <td>tc-1 plus Jingle call proposal and audio/video session signalling.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>tc-3</td>
        <td>Synchronized Total Conversation</td>
        <td>tc-2 plus real-time text or captions negotiated as part of the same Jingle session.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>tc-4</td>
        <td>Assistive context</td>
        <td>tc-3 plus consent-gated call-scoped context such as location, fallback state, caption source and service metadata.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Discovery' anchor='disco'>
    <p>An entity supporting this profile MUST advertise the base profile feature using &xep0030;:</p>
    <example caption='Base discovery feature'><![CDATA[
<feature var='urn:xmpp:total-conversation:0'/>
]]></example>
    <p>The base feature says that the entity understands the profile family. Actual level and modalities SHOULD be carried in a service discovery extension form.</p>
    <example caption='Discovery form'><![CDATA[
<query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'>
  <identity category='client' type='web' name='Example TC Client'/>
  <feature var='urn:xmpp:total-conversation:0'/>
  <x xmlns='jabber:x:data' type='result'>
    <field var='FORM_TYPE' type='hidden'>
      <value>urn:xmpp:total-conversation:0</value>
    </field>
    <field var='tc#level' type='list-single'>
      <value>tc-3</value>
    </field>
    <field var='tc#modalities' type='list-multi'>
      <value>chat</value>
      <value>rtt</value>
      <value>audio</value>
      <value>video</value>
      <value>caption</value>
    </field>
    <field var='tc#fallbacks' type='list-multi'>
      <value>xep-0301</value>
      <value>xep-0363</value>
    </field>
  </x>
</query>
]]></example>
    <p>If a client advertises <tt>urn:xmpp:total-conversation:0</tt> but omits one of the underlying features, peers MUST treat that omitted part as unsupported.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Profile Binding Model' anchor='binding'>
    <p>Call-scoped media and context MUST be bound by at least the peer JID, Jingle session ID and Jingle content name. A peer JID alone is not sufficient because a user can have multiple devices, browser sessions, simultaneous calls or fallback chat paths.</p>
    <example caption='Total Conversation content set'><![CDATA[
Jingle sid: call-123
  content audio     -> RTP audio
  content video     -> RTP video
  content text      -> synchronized real-time text or captions
  content location  -> optional call-scoped location
  content file      -> optional session-bound file transfer
]]></example>
    <p>If synchronized text is not negotiated but fallback &xep0301; is used, the user interface MUST show that the text is fallback text and not synchronized Jingle text.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Use Cases' anchor='usecases'>
    <section2 topic='Accessible video call' anchor='uc-accessible-call'>
      <p>A deaf or hard-of-hearing user starts a call where sign-language video, audio and typed real-time text are visible together. The client advertises tc-3 because the text is part of the call session.</p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Fallback real-time text' anchor='uc-fallback'>
      <p>A peer supports audio/video Jingle but not synchronized Jingle text. The client continues the call and uses &xep0301; for fallback RTT. The user interface shows fallback state.</p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Relay or interpreter service' anchor='uc-relay'>
      <p>A user joins a call with a relay, captioner or interpreter service. The client identifies caption source and language when known and keeps the assistive text visibly associated with the call.</p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Emergency-readiness experiment' anchor='uc-emergency'>
      <p>A client can represent an emergency-oriented Total Conversation profile using audio, video, real-time text, captions and call-scoped location. This profile does not define PSAP routing or legal emergency-service requirements.</p>
    </section2>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Archive and History' anchor='archive'>
    <p>Archives MUST NOT erase whether text was synchronized, call-bound or fallback. If an archive contains call-bound text or call summaries, clients SHOULD retain enough metadata to show the Jingle session ID, content name, text source and synchronization state.</p>
    <p>&xep0313; MAY store ordinary messages, real-time text fallback messages and archiveable call-history events. It MUST NOT be used to store raw RTP packets, WebRTC media streams, camera output or microphone output.</p>
    <p>Optional recordings, video messages, voice messages and transcript files are file/media objects and should use existing file-sharing or upload specifications with appropriate consent, encryption and retention metadata.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='User Interface Rules' anchor='ui'>
    <p>A Total Conversation client MUST make the following states visible to the user and available to assistive technologies where applicable.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Whether live text is active.</li>
      <li>Whether text is synchronized to the call or is fallback RTT.</li>
      <li>Whether captions are human, ASR, interpreter, translation or system generated when known.</li>
      <li>Whether audio and video are active, muted, held or failed.</li>
      <li>Whether call-scoped location is shared.</li>
      <li>Whether files or recordings are message attachments, session-bound transfers or external references.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Color alone MUST NOT be the only indicator for fallback, recording, emergency, muted, failed or caption-source state.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Business Rules' anchor='rules'>
    <ol>
      <li>A client MUST NOT advertise <tt>tc-3</tt> unless it can bind real-time text or captions to the same Jingle session as audio or video.</li>
      <li>A client MUST NOT advertise <tt>tc-4</tt> unless it can represent assistive context and user consent state.</li>
      <li>Fallback paths are allowed but MUST be visible.</li>
      <li>This profile is not a codec registry. Audio and video codec negotiation remains delegated to the relevant Jingle RTP and WebRTC mechanisms.</li>
      <li>This profile is not an emergency-services standard.</li>
    </ol>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Accessibility Considerations' anchor='access'>
    <p>This profile exists primarily because accessibility requires the conversation to be coherent. Deaf, hard-of-hearing, speech-impaired and mixed-hearing groups need to know whether text is typed by the other person, generated by ASR, entered by a captioner, translated, interpreted, delayed, synchronized to the call or fallback outside the call.</p>
    <p>Implementations SHOULD provide keyboard-operable call, text, media, file and location controls; accessible names for icon-only controls; focus order that follows the conversation flow; sufficient contrast; and visible fallback warnings that do not rely on color alone.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
    <p>This profile can combine sensitive media, text, files, location and service metadata. Implementations SHOULD use encrypted transport and end-to-end encryption where available.</p>
    <p>Downgrade attacks are important. If synchronized text falls back to ordinary &xep0301;, or call-scoped location falls back to global PEP location, the user MUST be informed.</p>
    <p>Received captions, ASR text, translations and location data MUST NOT be treated as verified facts unless additional trust and verification mechanisms exist.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Privacy Considerations' anchor='privacy'>
    <p>Total Conversation can expose partial text before a message is final, live speech through captions, contact availability, file metadata, location and call participation across multiple devices.</p>
    <p>Clients MUST ask for user consent before sending live location or enabling assistive services that involve third parties such as ASR, captioning, translation, relay or interpreter providers.</p>
    <p>Location sharing MUST stop when the call ends, when the user stops sharing, when permission is revoked, or when the source becomes stale.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
    <p>This document requires no interaction with the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority.</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
    <p>This specification requests registration of the following service discovery feature:</p>
    <example caption='Registered feature'><![CDATA[
urn:xmpp:total-conversation:0
]]></example>
    <p>This specification requests registration of the following XEP-0128 form type:</p>
    <example caption='Registered form type'><![CDATA[
FORM_TYPE = urn:xmpp:total-conversation:0
]]></example>
    <p>Initial form fields are:</p>
    <table caption='Total Conversation discovery form fields'>
      <tr>
        <th>Field</th>
        <th>Type</th>
        <th>Values</th>
        <th>Meaning</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>tc#level</td>
        <td>list-single</td>
        <td>tc-0, tc-1, tc-2, tc-3, tc-4</td>
        <td>Highest Total Conversation level the entity can honestly negotiate.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>tc#modalities</td>
        <td>list-multi</td>
        <td>chat, rtt, caption, audio, video, file, location, translation, interpreter</td>
        <td>Conversation modalities the entity can present or send.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>tc#fallbacks</td>
        <td>list-multi</td>
        <td>Protocol identifiers such as xep-0301, xep-0363 and xep-0080-pep</td>
        <td>Fallback paths the entity can use and expose to users.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='XML Schema' anchor='schema'>
    <p>This profile defines a discovery feature and XEP-0128 data form, but no standalone XML payload.</p>
  </section1>
</xep>
