<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep><header>
<title>Group Chat Reporting</title>
<abstract>This specification describes how a client can report abuse and spam in a MUC or other group chat context.</abstract>
&LEGALNOTICE;
<number>xxxx</number>
<status>ProtoXEP</status>
<type>Standards Track</type>
<sig>Standards</sig>
<approver>Council</approver>
<dependencies/>
<supersedes/>
<supersededby/>
<shortname>gcreport</shortname>
&mwild;
<revision>
<version>0.0.1</version>
<date>2026-03-31</date>
<initials>mjw</initials>
<remark>
</remark>
</revision>
</header>
<section1 topic="Introduction" anchor="intro">

<p>Abuse and spam are common issues on any open network. XMPP is no exception,
and we have a range of protocols and tools to tackle various aspects of the
problem. Until now, however, there has been no standard in-band way to report
abuse in group chats.</p>

<p>This specification describes a protocol to report messages as abuse/spam,
report problematic participants to group chat admins, and to report
problematic group chats to server admins.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Requirements" anchor="reqs">

<p>The requirements this specification aims to meet include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Providing a way for a participant to report problematic messages and
participants to group chat admins, so the admins can take appropriate action
(such as banning the user).</li>
<li>Providing a way to report problematic group chats to the admins of a service.</li>
</ul>

<p>The specification aims to reuse existing protocol containers which fit the
data being transported. For example, it uses the report syntax from &xep0377;.</p>

<p>The protocol is designed to work within the context of &xep0045; or any
group chat protocol that uses &xep0421; to identify occupants and uses JIDs to
identify group chats.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Use Cases" anchor="usecases">

<section2 topic="Reporting participants and messages" anchor="reporting-participants-and-messages">

<example  caption="Bad participant sends spam to a group chat"><![CDATA[<message to="chat@rooms.example.com" from="chat@rooms.example.com/spammer" type="groupchat">
    <body>Click here to win $$$$: https://malware.example/buy-now</body>
    <stanza-id id="019d29fc-bbcb-7920-93c2-64053721aa7b" by="chat@rooms.example.com" xmlns='urn:xmpp:sid:0'/>
</message>]]></example>

<p>A participant in the chat reports this message, e.g. so it can be moderated using &xep0425; and the sender banned.</p>

<example  caption="Good participant submits a report"><![CDATA[<iq type="set" to="chat@rooms.example.com" id="report1">
    <report-participant xmlns='urn:xmpp:gcreport:0'>
        <occupant-id xmlns="urn:xmpp:occupant-id:0" id="dd72603deec90a38ba552f7c68cbcc61bca202cd" />
        <report xmlns='urn:xmpp:reporting:1' reason='urn:xmpp:reporting:spam'>
            <stanza-id id="019d29fc-bbcb-7920-93c2-64053721aa7b" by="chat@rooms.example.com" xmlns='urn:xmpp:sid:0'/>
            <text xml:lang='en'>Malware distribution</text>
        </report>
    </report-participant>
</iq>]]></example>

<p>Reporting happens via an &lt;iq/&gt; of type 'set' containing a &lt;submit/&gt;
payload element qualified by the 'urn:xmpp:gcreport:0' namespace.</p>

<p>The &lt;submit/&gt; element MUST contain one &lt;occupant-id/&gt; (defined
in XEP-0421) which identifies the participant being reported.</p>

<p>It MUST also contain a single &lt;report/&gt; element, as defined by XEP-0377.</p>

<p>Per the rules of XEP-0377, the &lt;stanza-id/&gt; element is not required, but
SHOULD be included if the reporter is reporting a specific message. This can
help provide additional context to the recipients of the report, which helps
improve incident resolution times. When provided, the referenced stanza MUST
be a stanza sent by the reported participant, otherwise the server SHOULD
ignore it.</p>

</section2><section2 topic="Reporting chats" anchor="reporting-chats">

<p>In some cases, a user may want to report an entire group chat to the server
operator. For example, if the chat, its subject or administrators violate the
server’s policies.</p>

<example  caption="Concerned user reports a chat to the server"><![CDATA[<iq type='set' to='rooms.example.com' id='report1'>
    <report-chat xmlns='urn:xmpp:gcreport:0'>
        <jid>chat@rooms.example.com</jid>
        <report xmlns='urn:xmpp:reporting:1' reason='urn:xmpp:reporting:abuse'>
            <text xml:lang='en'>This channel violates the server's policy</text>
        </report>
    </report-chat>
</iq>]]></example>

<p>Reports about a group chat are sent via an &lt;iq/&gt; of type 'set' to the
MUC service JID. The payload of the stanza MUST be a &lt;report-chat/&gt;
element qualified by the 'urn:xmpp:gcreport:0' namespace.</p>

<p>Within this element MUST be a single &lt;jid/&gt; element (also in the
'urn:xmpp:gcreport:0' namespace).</p>

<p>Finally, a single &lt;report/&gt; element (as defined in XEP-0377) MUST be
included, specifying the reason for the report and any supporting evidence.</p>

</section2><section2 topic="Discovering support" anchor="discovering-support">

<p>Group chats which support reporting participants and services which support
reporting chats MUST both advertise the 'urn:xmpp:gcreport:0' feature in their
XEP-0030 service discovery features.</p>

</section2></section1><section1 topic="Business Rules" anchor="rules">

<p>Upon receipt of a report, a service SHOULD perform an appropriate action, such
as immediately notifying appropriate people in an appropriate manner, and/or
automatically moderating reported messages or hiding groups from public
listings. Any automated actions MUST be reversible upon review,to minimise the
consequences of malicious reports.</p>

<p>For reports about participants, JIDs with an affiliation of 'owner' or 'admin'
are generally the appropriate recipients of any report notifications.</p>

<p>For reports about chats, the responsible entity is usually the server
administrator</p>

<p>However, this XEP does not mandate any specific actions as the appropriate
action may depend on context such as the nature of the deployment, the
reporter and the reported entity.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Accessibility Considerations" anchor="access">

<p>No special accessibility concerns have been identified.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Internationalization Considerations" anchor="i18n">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Security Considerations" anchor="security">

<p>Implementations MUST consider various attack vectors in reporting systems
built upon this protocol. This includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Malicious/false reports</li>
<li>Flooding (rapid submission of reports; leading to overloading of the service or its operators)</li>
</ul>

<p>These issues can typically be tackled using standard techniques such as rate
limiting, and trust-based approaches based on the reporter (for example,
reports from long-standing affiliated members may take priority over reports
from new/untrusted users).</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Privacy Considerations" anchor="privacy">

<p>When processing reports, servers MUST consider the privacy of the reporter.
Appropriate measures would include anonymization (including at least removal
of the reporter’s JID) before forwarding the report to any third parties (such
as a server where the abuse originated). If abuse originates from a remote
server (e.g. a reported user hosts their account there), it cannot be assumed
that the remote server can necessarily be trusted.</p>

<p>Likewise, the privacy of reported entities MUST also be considered - not least
because false and malicious reports are entirely possible within this
protocol. Servers MUST NOT cause any private data to be exposed to untrusted
entities in response to a report.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="XMPP Registrar Considerations" anchor="registrar">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Design Considerations" anchor="design">

<p>This document aims to fill a gap in spam/abuse reporting, which already works
well for direct (one-to-one) chats. It reuses existing protocols which have
already been widely implemented and deployed.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="XML Schema" anchor="schema">

<p>TBD.</p>
</section1>
</xep>

