<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep><header>
<title>Occupant Mute Synchronization</title>
<abstract>Allows synchronizing a list of muted group chat participants between multiple clients.</abstract>
&LEGALNOTICE;
<number>xxxx</number>
<status>ProtoXEP</status>
<type>Standards Track</type>
<sig>Standards</sig>
<approver>Council</approver>
<dependencies/>
<supersedes/>
<supersededby/>
<shortname>mutesync</shortname>
&mwild;
<revision>
<version>0.0.1</version>
<date>2026-03-31</date>
<initials>mjw</initials>
<remark>
</remark>
</revision>
</header>
<section1 topic="Introduction" anchor="intro">

<p>For blocking remote users, XMPP already supports &xep0191; which uses a shared
account-wide blocklist. However, in the context of group chats this is
inadequate - it would allow blocking the entire group chat (which is sometimes
useful) but does not allow reliably blocking individual participants within a
chat.</p>

<p>This specification describes a mechanism through which a user can block (also
called 'muting' or 'ignoring') a group chat participant and have this
synchronized across all their clients.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Requirements" anchor="reqs">

<ul>
<li>Allow a user to mute a participant in a way that works reliably across all their devices</li>
<li>Muting should work even in semi-anonymous chats where the user does not know the participant’s real JID</li>
<li>It should work even if the muted participant rejoins or changes their nickname</li>
<li>Past messages should be able to be hidden retrospectively</li>
<li>The ability for clients to show that a message was sent to the chat from a muted participant (without showing the message contents)</li>
<li>Clients should be able to selectively reveal the contents of such messages (if the user requests that)</li>
</ul>

<p>To achieve these things, the protocol relies on client-side muting based on
&xep0421; with synchronization via &xep0402;</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Use Cases" anchor="usecases">

<section2 topic="Client adds new muted participant" anchor="client-adds-new-muted-participant">

<p>To add a new mute, the client updates the XEP-0402 bookmark for the group chat
to include a &lt;muted/&gt; element qualified by the 'urn:xmpp:muted:0'
namespace in the &lt;extensions/&gt; element of the bookmark.</p>

<p>The &lt;muted/&gt; element contains zero or more &lt;mute/&gt; elements. Each
&lt;mute/&gt; element MUST have an 'id' attribute set to the XEP-0421 occupant
identifier of an occupant that is to be muted.</p>

<example  caption="Client adds a participant mute to the bookmark"><![CDATA[<iq from='juliet@capulet.lit/balcony' type='set' id='mute2'>
  <pubsub xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/pubsub'>
    <publish node='urn:xmpp:bookmarks:1'>
      <item id='orchard@conference.shakespeare.lit'>
        <conference xmlns='urn:xmpp:bookmarks:1'
                    name='The Orchard'
                    autojoin='true'>
          <extensions>
            <muted xmlns='urn:xmpp:mute:0'>
                <mute occupant='dd72603deec90a38ba552f7c68cbcc61bca202cd'/>
            </muted>
          </extensions>
        </conference>
      </item>
    </publish>
    <publish-options>
      <x xmlns='jabber:x:data' type='submit'>
        <field var='FORM_TYPE' type='hidden'>
          <value>http://jabber.org/protocol/pubsub#publish-options</value>
        </field>
        <field var='pubsub#persist_items'>
          <value>true</value>
        </field>
        <field var='pubsub#max_items'>
          <value>max</value>
        </field>
        <field var='pubsub#send_last_published_item'>
          <value>never</value>
        </field>
        <field var='pubsub#access_model'>
          <value>whitelist</value>
        </field>
      </x>
    </publish-options>
  </pubsub>
</iq>]]></example>

</section2></section1><section1 topic="Business Rules" anchor="rules">

<p>Clients SHOULD maintain a local list of muted participants in each group chat
and keep it synchronized with the bookmarks (publishing local changes, and
reacting to changes received from other clients).</p>

<p>If the &lt;muted/&gt; element becomes empty, it SHOULD be removed from the
bookmark. Clients receiving bookmarks with an empty or absent &lt;muted/&gt;
element MUST assume there are no muted participants within that chat.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Accessibility Considerations" anchor="access">

<p>There are no significant accessibility considerations for this protocol.
This XEP does not mandate any particular UI for how messages from muted
participants are handled. However, some guidance is provided to aid
consistency between implementations and reduce the potential for confusion.</p>

<p>In general, clients SHOULD display an indication that a message was received
(but not displayed) from a muted participant, to reduce confusion when
conversations between other users and the muted participant occur.</p>

<p>Clients MAY also provide a way for a user to temporarily reveal the contents
of a muted message, to provide necessary context.</p>

<p>Clients SHOULD retroactively hide messages from muted participants, and
similarly unhide them when a participant is unmuted.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Internationalization Considerations" anchor="i18n">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Security Considerations" anchor="security">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Privacy Considerations" anchor="privacy">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="XMPP Registrar Considerations" anchor="registrar">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Design Considerations" anchor="design">

<p>Alternative approaches were considered but rejected. Some users have tried
using XEP-0191 to block occupant JIDs, and implementations have been tweaked
to ensure this works as well as it can. However, this approach has several
problems:</p>

<ul>
<li>If servers reply with error bounces to blocked messages, this bounce can be
interpreted as a delivery error by the group chat server, and result in the
user being kicked from the chat.</li>
<li>While live messages are blocked by XEP-0191, they may still be fetched by
clients from the history (e.g. via XEP-0313).</li>
<li>Blocks are based on nickname, and therefore can be bypassed when the blocked
participant changes their nickname.</li>
<li>Client ability to retroactively apply/remove blocks or temporarily reveal
blocked messages are not possible with blocking.</li>
</ul>

<p>Server-side muting (in the group chat server or the user’s own server) was
considered, but has similar issues relating to history availability, reliable
sync, and so on.</p>

<p>The final approach that was considered was a separate PEP node for mutes.
However, mutes are scoped to a group chat already by the way that occupant IDs
are. This means it makes sense to store a per-chat list of mutes. We already
have per-chat information storage in XEP-0402, so it made a lot of sense to
move this information into the bookmark to avoid the two stores getting out of
sync.</p>

<p>A downside of the approach used in this specification is that you can’t sync
mutes for a chat without having a bookmark for it. This generally seems to be
a non-issue, as practically all modern clients already automatically create
bookmarks for chats they join as a matter of course, to ensure consistency
across restarts and across clients.</p>
</section1>
</xep>

