<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
        <!ENTITY envelope "&lt;envelope/&gt;">
        <!ENTITY payload "&lt;payload/&gt;">
        <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "xep.ent">
        <!ENTITY ns "urn:xmpp:ppqm:1">
        <!ENTITY nsdevices "urn:xmpp:ppqm:1:devices">
        <!ENTITY nsbundles "urn:xmpp:ppqm:1:bundles">
        <!ENTITY pqxdh "<span class='ref'><link url='https://signal.org/docs/specifications/pqxdh/'>Post-Quantum Extended Diffie-Hellman (PQXDH)</link></span> <note>PQXDH: THe PQXDH Key Agreement Protocol &lt;<link url='https://signal.org/docs/specifications/pqxdh/'>https://signal.org/docs/specifications/pqxdh/</link>&gt;.</note>">
        <!ENTITY mlkem "<span class='ref'><link url='https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/fips/203/final'>ML-KEM (FIPS 203)</link></span> <note>ML-KEM: Module-Lattice-Based Key Encapsulation Mechanism &lt;<link url='https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/fips/203/final'>https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/fips/203/final</link>&gt;.</note>">
        <!ENTITY aes "<span class='ref'><link url='https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/fips/197/final'>AES (FIPS 197)</link></span> <note>AES: Advanced Encryption Standard &lt;<link url='https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/fips/197/final'>https://csrc.nist.gov/pubs/fips/197/final</link>&gt;.</note>">
        <!ENTITY shor "<span class='ref'><link url='https://doi.org/10.1109/sfcs.1994.365700'>Shor's Algorithm</link></span> <note>Algorithms for quantum computation: discrete logarithms and factoring &lt;<link url='https://doi.org/10.1109/sfcs.1994.365700'>https://doi.org/10.1109/sfcs.1994.365700</link>&gt;.</note>">
        %ents;
        ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
  <header>
    <title>PPQM Encryption</title>
    <abstract>
      This specification defines a protocol for post-quantum secure end-to-end encryption in one-to-one chats, as well as
      group chats where each participant may have multiple clients per account.
    </abstract>
    &LEGALNOTICE;
    <number>XXXX</number>
    <status>Experimental</status>
    <type>Standards Track</type>
    <sig>Standards</sig>
    <approver>Council</approver>
    <dependencies>
      <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0060</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0163</spec>
      <spec>XEP-0420</spec>
    </dependencies>
    <supersedes/>
    <supersededby/>
    <shortname>PPQM</shortname>
    <author>
      <firstname>Jamieson</firstname>
      <surname>O'Reilly</surname>
      <email>jamieson@privt.com</email>
    </author>
    <author>
      <firstname>Ron Lauren</firstname>
      <surname>Hombre</surname>
      <email>ronlauren@privt.com</email>
    </author>
    <author>
      <firstname>Hiren</firstname>
      <surname>Vavadiya</surname>
      <email>hiren@privt.com</email>
    </author>
    <revision>
      <version>0.1.0</version>
      <date>2024-08-27</date>
      <initials>jor</initials>
      <remark>
        <p>
          Initial version based on &xep0384; with updates for post-quantum security using Module-Lattice-Based Key
          Encapsulation Mechanism (ML-KEM).
        </p>
      </remark>
    </revision>
  </header>

  <section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
    <section2 topic='Motivation' anchor='intro-motivation'>
      <p>
        The advancement of quantum computing poses a significant threat to classical encryption schemes currently in use.
        While protocols like &xep0364; messaging and &xep0027; have provided encryption in the past, they are not
        equipped to withstand the power of quantum computers. The quantum algorithm &shor; can efficiently
        break the classical encryption algorithms in use today which necessitates a transition to post-quantum
        cryptographic algorithms.
      </p>
      <p>
        <strong>PPQM Encryption</strong> (<em>Privt. Post-Quantum Multi-End Message and Object Encryption</em>) is
        designed to address these emerging threats by incorporating the post-quantum secure algorithm
        &mlkem;(<em>historically CRYSTALS-Kyber v3.02</em>) to ensure that communication remains secure and private even
        in the face of inevitable future quantum computing advancements.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Overview' anchor='intro-overview'>
      <p>
        PPQM builds upon the strengths of Signal's &pqxdh; and the openness of XMPP's
        &xep0384;(<em>based upon &x3dh;</em>). Specifically, PPQM utilizes ML-KEM to generate shared secret keys that will
        remain secure under an active quantum adversarial threat. It is then fed into the X3DH Protocol as another layer
        of security. It is correct to say that this is a hybrid as the classical &xeddsa; is used alongside the
        post-quantum ML-KEM.
      </p>
      <p>
        Like OMEMO, PPQM supports multi-end message and object encryption, allowing secure message synchronization across
        multiple devices. An ephemeral key is used to encrypt each message, and headers containing the necessary
        parts of the ephemeral keys are individually encrypted for each recipient device. These headers and the encrypted
        payload are transmitted in a <tt>&lt;message&gt;</tt> stanza.
      </p>
      <p>
        PPQM maintains compatibility with existing XMPP standards by using &xep0060; and &xep0163; to manage and
        distribute key material securely.
      </p>
    </section2>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Requirements' anchor='reqs'>
    <p>
      As a result of XMPP's federated nature, messages may pass through multiple servers. It is crucial to secure
      communications from any intermediate hosts, especially in a post-quantum world. PPQM aims to provide robust
      end-to-end encryption that remains secure even against quantum-capable adversaries.</p>
    <p>
      PPQM provides the following guarantees under the threat model described in the next section:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Confidentiality: Only the sender and receiver can read the content of a message, secured by post-quantum
        ML-KEM which is believed to be resistant against quantum computers.
      </li>
      <li>
        Forward Secrecy: Compromised key material does not compromise previous message exchanges, ensured by the X3DH
        algorithm.
      </li>
      <li>
        Break-in Recovery: A session compromised due to key material leakage will recover after a few communication
        rounds as a property of X3DH.
      </li>
      <li>
        Authentication: Each peer can authenticate the sender or receiver of a message, leveraging Ed25519 for signatures.
      </li>
      <li>
        Integrity: Each peer can ensure that a message has not been altered by any intermediate node due to the
        AES-256-GCM symmetric encryption applied to the <tt>&lt;message&gt;</tt> stanza.
      </li>
      <li>
        Deniability: PPQM aims to provide deniability in a similar fashion to &xep0384;, though post-quantum deniability
        is an area of active research.
      </li>
      <li>
        Asynchronicity: The protocol does not rely on the online status of any participant, ensuring usability in
        asynchronous messaging scenarios.`
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>PPQM is not intended to protect against the following scenarios:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        An attacker with permanent access to your device. In this case, the attacker could extract decrypted messages from
        the device.
      </li>
      <li>
        Loss of a device where an attacker can read messages on the notification screen.
      </li>
      <li>
        Denial-of-service attacks of any kind.
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Trust management remains a challenging topic, and is considered out of scope for this document.
    </p>
    <section2 topic='Threat Model' anchor='reqs-threat-model'>
      <p>
        The use case for PPQM is to protect the content of conversations against quantum-capable adversaries, including
        scenarios where servers cannot be trusted to maintain the confidentiality of the message content. This includes
        scenarios such as sharing sensitive corporate information or exchanging intimate messages that must remain
        confidential even from the server administrators.
      </p>
      <p>
        PPQM protects against passive and active attackers who can read, modify, replay, delay, and delete messages.
        However, PPQM does not protect against attacks based on metadata or traffic analysis.
      </p>
    </section2>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Glossary' anchor='glossary'>
    <dl>
      <di>
        <dt>AES-256-GCM</dt>
        <dd>
          A Galois/Counter Mode variant of the Advanced Encryption Standard with key size of 256 bits.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>HMAC-SHA-256</dt>
        <dd>
          Hash-based Message Authentication Code using SHA2-256 as the hashing function.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>HKDF-SHA-256</dt>
        <dd>
          An HMAC-based Key Derivation Function using SHA2-256 as the hashing function.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>ML-KEM</dt>
        <dd>
          <em>Module-Lattice-Based Key Encapsulation Mechanism</em> which is based upon CRYSTALS-Kyber V3.02 and
          standardized as NIST FIPS 203. The security of this algorithm hangs upon the computation difficulty of the
          <em>Module Learning with Errors</em> problem for both classical and quantum computers. This is used as the
          KEMPreKey in this protocol.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>ML-KEM-1024</dt>
        <dd>
          An ML-KEM parameter set with claimed security category of 5. According to the FIPS 203 paper, this has a
          Random Bit Generator strength of 256.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>Device</dt>
        <dd>
          A communication endpoint, i.e., a specific client instance with a working PPQM implementation.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>PPQM element</dt>
        <dd>
          An <tt>&lt;encrypted&gt;</tt> element in the <tt>&ns;</tt> namespace.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>Bundle</dt>
        <dd>
          A collection of publicly accessible data used in the post-quantum extended triple diffie-hellman protocol,
          including the public IdentityKey, a list of single-use Curve25519 PreKeys, and a list of single-use KEMPreKeys
          with their corresponding signatures.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>rid</dt>
        <dd>
          The device id of the intended recipient of the containing <tt>&lt;key&gt;</tt>.
        </dd>
      </di>
      <di>
        <dt>sid</dt>
        <dd>
          The device id of the sender of the containing PPQM element.
        </dd>
      </di>
    </dl>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Protocol Definition' anchor='protocol'>
    <section2 topic='Overview' anchor='protocol-overview'>
      <p>
        This protocol utilizes the Double Ratchet encryption scheme alongside a post-quantum KEM in the Triple
        Diffie-Hellman algorithm. The following sections provide the technical details necessary to build an
        implementation of the PPQM protocol.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Key Exchange' anchor='protocol-key_exchange'>
      <p>
        The key exchange in PPQM is based on a modified version of the X3DH key agreement protocol, updated to incorporate
        post-quantum secure components:
      </p>
      <dl>
        <di>
          <dt>kem</dt>
          <dd>ML-KEM-1024</dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>hash function</dt>
          <dd>SHA-256 also known as SHA2-256</dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>info string</dt>
          <dd>&quot;PPQM X3DH&quot;</dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>signed PreKey rotation period</dt>
          <dd>
            Signed PreKeys SHOULD be rotated periodically, from once a week to once a month.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>time to retain the private key of the old signed PreKey after a round of rotation</dt>
          <dd>
            The private key SHOULD be retained for an additional rotation period to accommodate delayed messages still
            using the old signed PreKey.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>number of PreKeys to include in the bundle</dt>
          <dd>
            The bundle SHOULD always contain around 100 PreKeys.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>minimum number of PreKeys to include in the bundle</dt>
          <dd>
            The bundle MUST contain at least 25 PreKeys.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>number of KEMPreKeys to include in the bundle</dt>
          <dd>
            The bundle SHOULD always contain around 100 KEMPreKeys. This number MUST equal the number of PreKeys in the
            bundle in order to reduce the number of collisions for both.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>minimum number of KEMPreKeys to include in the bundle</dt>
          <dd>
            The bundle MUST contain at least 25 KEMPreKeys.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>usage of PreKeys and KEMPreKeys</dt>
          <dd>
            All key exchanges MUST use a PreKey and a KEMPreKey. Any key exchanges that do not use a PreKey and a
            KEMPreKey MUST be rejected. This is a basic requirement of PPQM.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>associated data</dt>
          <dd>
            The Associated Data (AD) is created by concatenating the IdentityKeys of Alice and Bob:
            <tt>AD = Encode(IK_ALICE) || Encode(IK_BOB)</tt>. In this order, <tt>Alice</tt> <em>initiated</em> the key
            exchange while <tt>Bob</tt> <em>accepted</em> the key exchange.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>XEdDSA</dt>
          <dd>PPQM does not mandate the usage of &xeddsa; with &x3dh; for the IdentityKey. Instead, there are three simple
            rules that implementations MUST follow:
            <ol>
              <li>
                Implementations must use the birational map between the curves Curve25519 and Ed25519 to convert the public
                part of the IdentityKey whenever required, as defined in &rfc7748; (on page 5).
              </li>
              <li>
                Implementations must be able to perform X25519 (ECDH on Curve25519) using the IdentityKey.
              </li>
              <li>
                Implementations must be able to create EdDSA-compatible signatures on the curve Ed25519 using the
                IdentityKey.
              </li>
            </ol>
            There are essentially two ways in which libraries can fulfill these requirements:
            <ol>
              <li>
                Libraries can use a Curve25519 key pair as their internal IdentityKey. In this case, the IdentityKey can be
                used for X25519 directly, and XEdDSA has to be used to produce EdDSA-compatible signatures. Note that
                libsignal by default does <strong>NOT</strong> use XEdDSA. libsignal <em>includes</em> XEdDSA though and has
                to be modified to use that to be compatible with OMEMO.
              </li>
              <li>
                Libraries can use an Ed25519 key pair as their internal IdentityKey. In this case, the IdentityKey can
                create EdDSA-compatible signatures directly, and has to be converted first to perform X25519.
              </li>
            </ol>
            Note that this decision is purely local to each client and PPQM library. The public key is ALWAYS transferred
            in its Ed25519 form and only valid EdDSA signatures are transferred. The choice between Curve25519 and Ed25519
            affects the definition of the <tt>Sig(PK, M)</tt> and <tt>DH(PK1, PK2)</tt> functions as defined below.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>DH(PK1, PK2)</dt>
          <dd>
            The original definition of <tt>DH(PK1, PK2)</tt> found in the X3DH specification applies with one exception:
            if the IdentityKey pair is chosen to be an Ed25519 key pair and either <tt>PK1</tt> or <tt>PK2</tt>
            corresponds to the IdentityKey, the respective key first has to be converted into its Curve25519 equivalent
            (see above). This conversion is implemented for example by <tt>libsodium</tt>, which exports the conversion as
            <tt>crypto_sign_ed25519_sk_to_curve25519</tt> and <tt>crypto_sign_ed25519_pk_to_curve25519</tt> for the
            private and public key, respectively (documented on <link url="https://download.libsodium.org/doc/advanced/ed25519-curve25519">libsodium.org</link>).
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>Encode(PK)</dt>
          <dd>The public part of the IdentityKey pair is encoded as defined in &rfc8032;. Note that the IdentityKey is
            always transferred in its Ed25519 form. When using a Curve25519 key pair internally, the public key has to be
            converted to Ed25519 first. Curve25519 public keys are encoded using the little-endian encoding of the
            u-coordinate as specified in &rfc7748;.
          </dd>
        </di>
      </dl>
      <p>
        The key exchange is performed just-in-time when sending the first message to a device, ensuring that each key
        exchange message also contains encrypted content as produced by the post-quantum Double Ratchet encryption scheme
        described below.
      </p>
      <p>
        In essence, PPQM is extremely similar to OMEMO except for the added KEMPreKey in the X3DH Protocol.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Double Ratchet' anchor='protocol-double_ratchet'>
      <p>
        NOTE: <tt>PPQMMessage.proto</tt>, <tt>PPQMAuthenticatedMessage.proto</tt> and <tt>PPQMKeyExchange.proto</tt> refer
        to the protobuf structures as defined in the <link url="#protobuf-schema">Protobuf Schemas</link>.
      </p>
      <p>
        The &doubleratchet; encryption scheme is adapted to use post-quantum key material. PPQM uses this protocol with
        the following parameters/settings:
      </p>
      <dl>
        <di>
          <dt>ratchet initialization</dt>
          <dd>
            The Double Ratchet is initialized using the shared secret, associated data, and public keys as yielded by the
            X3DH Protocol, as explained in the Double Ratchet specification. The ephemeral key pair used by the key
            agreement protocol is stored with the session.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>MAX_SKIP</dt>
          <dd>
            As with OMEMO, storing skipped message keys can introduce potential DoS attacks. It is RECOMMENDED to limit
            the storage to 1000 skipped message keys per session. Secondly, a maximum number of skipped message keys has
            to be limited, or else, a malicious actor could make the receiving device calculate the integer limit of
            skipped message keys.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>deletion policy for skipped message keys</dt>
          <dd>
            PPQM follows the same guidelines as OMEMO, with skipped message keys being discarded on a FIFO basis when the
            limit is reached. All implementations MUST NOT keep message keys around forever and discard them based on
            deterministic events except time.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>authentication tag truncation</dt>
          <dd>
            Authentication tags are truncated to 16 bytes/128 bits.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>CONCAT(ad, header)</dt>
          <dd>
            <tt>CONCAT(ad, header) = ad || PPQMMessage.proto(header)</tt>
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>KDF_RK(rk, dh_out)</dt>
          <dd>
            HKDF-SHA-256 using the root key (rk) as HKDF salt, the output of a Diffie-Hellman (dh_out) as HKDF input
            material, and &quot;PPQM Root Chain&quot; as HKDF info.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>KDF_CK(ck)</dt>
          <dd>
            HMAC-SHA-256 using a chain key (ck) as the HMAC key, with specified constants for message key and chain key
            derivation.
          </dd>
        </di>
        <di>
          <dt>ENCRYPT(mk, plaintext, associated_data)</dt>
          <dd>
            The encryption step uses authenticated encryption consisting of AES-256-GCM with HMAC-SHA-256.
            <ol>
              <li>
                Use HKDF-SHA-256 to generate 80 bytes of output from the message key by providing mk as HKDF input, 256
                zero-bits as HKDF salt and &quot;OMEMO Message Key Material&quot; as HKDF info.
              </li>
              <li>
                Divide the HKDF output into a 32-byte encryption key, a 32-byte authentication key and a 16 byte IV.
              </li>
              <li>
                Encrypt the plaintext (which consists of a 32 bytes key and 16 bytes HMAC as specified in the section
                about <link url="#protocol-message_encryption">Message Encryption</link>) using AES-256-GCM with no
                padding, using the encryption key and IV derived in the previous step.
              </li>
              <li>
                Split the associated data as returned by <tt>CONCAT</tt> into the original ad and the
                <tt>PPQMMessage.proto</tt> structure.
              </li>
              <li>
                Add the ciphertext to the <tt>PPQMMessage.proto</tt> structure.
              </li>
              <li>
                Serialize the <tt>PPQMMessage.proto</tt> structure into a parseable byte array. To avoid potential
                problems regarding non-uniqueness of the serialization, make sure to only serialize <em>once</em> and to
                use that exact byte sequence in the following steps.
              </li>
              <li>
                Concatenate the ad and the <tt>PPQMMessage.proto</tt> structure into a parseable byte array. The result
                builds the HMAC input material for the next step.
              </li>
              <li>
                Calculate the HMAC-SHA-256 using the authentication key and the input material as derived in the steps
                above. Truncate the output of the HMAC to 16 bytes/128 bits.
              </li>
              <li>
                Put the serialized <tt>PPQMMessage.proto</tt> structure and the HMAC into a new
                <tt>PPQMAuthenticatedMessage.proto</tt> structure.
              </li>
            </ol>
          </dd>
        </di>
      </dl>
      <p>
        Further information on these functions can be found in the &doubleratchet; specification.
      </p>
      <p>
        If the message requires a key exchange, the key exchange data is placed into a new <tt>PPQMKeyExchange.proto</tt>
        structure together with the <tt>PPQMAuthenticatedMessage.proto</tt> structure.
      </p>
      <p>
        To account for lost and out-of-order messages, <tt>PPQMKeyExchange.proto</tt> structures are sent until a response
        by the recipient confirms successful key exchange. Subsequent messages use the stored header until confirmation is
        received.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Message Encryption' anchor='protocol-message_encryption'>
      <p>
        The contents are encrypted and authenticated using a combination of AES-256-GCM and HMAC-SHA-256.
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          Generate 32 bytes using a CSPRNG, effectively called <tt>key</tt> for the rest of the specification.
        </li>
        <li>
          Use HKDF-SHA-256 to generate 80 bytes of output from the <tt>key</tt> by providing the key as HKDF input, 256
          zero-bits as HKDF salt and &quot;PPQM Payload&quot; as HKDF info.
        </li>
        <li>
          Divide the HKDF output into a 32-byte encryption key, a 32-byte authentication key and a 16 byte IV.
        </li>
        <li>
          Encrypt the plaintext using AES-256-GCM with no padding, using the encryption key and IV derived in the previous
          step.
        </li>
        <li>
          Calculate the HMAC-SHA-256 using the authentication key and the ciphertext from the previous steps. Truncate the
          output of the HMAC to 16 bytes/128 bits by cutting off excess bytes from the end.
        </li>
        <li>
          Concatenate the <tt>key</tt> and the HMAC, encrypt them using the Double Ratchet as specified above, once for
          each intended recipient. This yields one <tt>PPQMKeyExchange</tt> or <tt>PPQMAuthenticatedMessage</tt> per
          recipient device.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Message Decryption' anchor='protocol-message_decryption'>
      <p>
        The contents are decrypted by reversing the encryption steps.
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          Decrypt the key and HMAC from the <tt>PPQMKeyExchange</tt> or <tt>PPQMAuthenticatedMessage</tt>, encrypted using
          the Double Ratchet belonging to this device.
        </li>
        <li>
          Use HKDF-SHA-256 to generate 80 bytes of output from the <tt>key</tt> by providing the <tt>key</tt> as HKDF
          input, 256 zero-bits as HKDF salt and &quot;PPQM Payload&quot; as HKDF info.
        </li>
        <li>
          Divide the HKDF output into a 32-byte encryption key, a 32-byte authentication key and a 16 byte IV.
        </li>
        <li>
          Verify the (truncated) HMAC-SHA-256 using the authentication key derived in the previous step and the
          ciphertext.
        </li>
        <li>
          Decrypt the ciphertext using AES-256-GCM with no padding, using the encryption key and IV derived in the
          previous steps.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section2>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Use Cases' anchor='usecases'>
    <section2 topic='Setup' anchor='usecases-setup'>
      <p>
        To participate in PPQM Encrypted chats, clients need to set up a PPQM library and generate a device id, which is a
        randomly generated integer between 1 and 2^31 - 1. This device id MUST be unique for the account.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Discovering peer support' anchor='usecases-discovering'>
      <p>
        To determine whether a given contact supports PPQM, the devices node in PEP is consulted. Devices MUST subscribe
        to <tt>&nsdevices;</tt> via PEP to stay informed of new devices.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Announcing support' anchor='usecases-announcing'>
      <section3 topic='Device list' anchor='devices'>
        <p>
          A device must announce itself by adding its device id to the devices PEP node. The node’s access model must be set
          to ‘open’ for this purpose.
        </p>
      </section3>
      <section3 topic='Bundles' anchor='bundles'>
        <p>
          A device must publish its IdentityKey, a Signed PreKey, a list of PreKeys, and a list of KEMPreKeys in a bundle.
          This is stored in the <tt>&nsbundles;</tt> node, which must support multiple items.
        </p>
      </section3>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Building a session' anchor='usecases-building'>
      <p>
        To build a session with a device, fetch its bundle information and use a random PreKey and KEMPreKey to establish
        a PPQM session.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Sending a message' anchor='usecases-messagesend'>
      <section3 topic='SCE Profile' anchor='sce'>
        <p>
          A PPQM SCE &envelope; element MUST contain an &lt;rpad/&gt; affix element. Other optional elements include
          &lt;time/&gt; and &lt;from/&gt;.
        </p>
      </section3>
      <section3 topic='Encryption' anchor='encrypt'>
        <p>
          The &envelope; element is encrypted as described in the Message Encryption section.
        </p>
      </section3>
      <section3 topic='Message structure description' anchor='message-structure-description'>
        <p>
          A PPQM encrypted message includes an &lt;encrypted&gt; element in the <tt>&ns;</tt> namespace. It contains a
          &lt;header&gt; and a &payload; element.
        </p>
        <p>Empty PPQM messages omit the &lt;payload&gt; element, containing only the &lt;header&gt;.</p>
      </section3>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Receiving a message' anchor='usecases-receiving'>
      <p>
        Upon receiving a PPQM element, check if it contains a &lt;keys&gt; element for your device. If so, proceed with
        decryption or session establishment as necessary.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Opt-out' anchor='opt-out'>
      <p>
        An account can signal its desire to stop PPQM communication by sending a &lt;opt-out/&gt; element qualified by the
        <tt>&ns;</tt> namespace.
      </p>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Group Chats' anchor='group-chats'>
      <section3 topic='Retrieving and maintaining members list' anchor='members-list'>
        <p>Retrieve the members list when joining a group chat to determine recipients of PPQM messages.</p>
      </section3>
      <section3 topic='Fetching devices and bundles' anchor='group-fetch'>
        <p>Fetch device lists and bundles for each member before sending a message.</p>
      </section3>
      <section3 topic='Sending a message' anchor='group-send'>
        <p>PPQM group messages are similar to 1:1 messages but include multiple &lt;keys&gt; elements for each participant.</p>
      </section3>
    </section2>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Business Rules' anchor='rules'>
    <p>
      Before publishing a new device id, ensure it is unique.
    </p>
    <p>
      When building sessions, the PreKey id and the KEMPreKey id taken by the client MUST be the same in order to
      guarantee that both PreKey and KEMPreKey are available. This avoids a situation where a PreKey is valid but the
      KEMPreKey has already been used but the bundle has yet to be updated. To further ensure this, the number of PreKeys
      and the KEMPreKeys published in the bundle MUST always match.
    </p>
    <p>
      After receiving a PPQMKeyExchange and successfully building a session, respond with an empty PPQM message to notify
      the sender.
    </p>
    <p>
      Handle decryption failures with care, ignoring repeated messages but notifying users of other failures.
    </p>
    <p>
      Postpone private key deletion until message catch-up is complete. Manually replace broken sessions as needed.
    </p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Implementation Notes' anchor='impl'>
    <section2 topic='Server side requirements' anchor='server-side'>
      <p>
        While PPQM uses a Pubsub Service (&xep0060;) on the user’s account it has more requirements than those defined in
        &xep0163;. The requirements are:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          The pubsub service MUST persist node items, i.e., the <link url='https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0060.html#features'>feature 'persistent-items'</link>
          is announced by the service.
        </li>
        <li>
          The pubsub service MUST support publishing options as defined in <link url='https://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0060.html#publisher-publish-options'><cite>XEP-0060</cite> §7.1.5</link>.
        </li>
        <li>
          The pubsub service MUST support 'max' as a value for the 'pubsub#persist_items' node configuration.
        </li>
        <li>
          The pubsub service MUST support the 'open' access model for node configuration and 'pubsub#access_model' as a
          publish option.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        Furthermore, the server MUST be able to adequately handle the large size of the bundle in a reasonable amount of
        time. Servers with low bandwidth MUST not declare themselves PPQM-compatible. A conservative 50kbps MUST at least
        be configured to ensure seamless session building.
      </p>
    </section2>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
    <p>
      Clients must not use a newly built session without user intervention. Trust decisions should involve fingerprint
      verification. Avoid automatic session creation following decryption errors.
    </p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
    <p>This document requires no interaction with the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).</p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
    <section2 topic='Protocol Namespaces' anchor='namespaces'>
      <p>This specification defines the following XMPP namespaces:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>&ns;</li>
      </ul>
    </section2>
    <section2 topic='Protocol Versioning' anchor='versioning'>
      &NSVER;
    </section2>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='XML Schema' anchor='schema'>
    <code><![CDATA[
<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<xs:schema xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema'
           targetNamespace=']]>&ns;<![CDATA['
           xmlns=']]>&ns;<![CDATA['>

    <xs:element name='encrypted'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:all>
                <xs:element ref='header'/>
                <xs:element ref='payload' minOccurs='0' maxOccurs='1'/>
            </xs:all>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='payload' type='xs:base64Binary'/>

    <xs:element name='header'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence maxOccurs='unbounded'>
                <xs:element ref='keys'/>
            </xs:sequence>
            <xs:attribute name='sid' type='xs:unsignedInt'/>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='keys'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence maxOccurs='unbounded'>
                <xs:element ref='key'/>
            </xs:sequence>
            <xs:attribute name='jid' type='xs:string' use='required'/>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='key'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:simpleContent>
                <xs:extension base='xs:base64Binary'>
                    <xs:attribute name='rid' type='xs:unsignedInt' use='required'/>
                    <xs:attribute name='kex' type='xs:boolean' default='false'/>
                </xs:extension>
            </xs:simpleContent>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='devices'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence maxOccurs='unbounded'>
                <xs:element ref='device'/>
            </xs:sequence>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='device'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:attribute name='id' type='xs:unsignedInt' use='required'/>
            <xs:attribute name='label' type='xs:string'/>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='bundle'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:all>
                <xs:element ref='spk'/>
                <xs:element ref='spks'/>
                <xs:element ref='ik'/>
                <xs:element ref='prekeys'/>
                <xs:element ref='kemprekeys'/>
            </xs:all>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='spk'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:simpleContent>
                <xs:extension base='xs:base64Binary'>
                    <xs:attribute name='id' type='xs:unsignedInt' use='required'/>
                </xs:extension>
            </xs:simpleContent>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='spks' type='xs:base64Binary'/>
    <xs:element name='ik' type='xs:base64Binary'/>

    <xs:element name='prekeys'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence minOccurs='25' maxOccurs='unbounded'>
                <xs:element ref='pk'/>
            </xs:sequence>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='pk'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:simpleContent>
                <xs:extension base='xs:base64Binary'>
                    <xs:attribute name='id' type='xs:unsignedInt' use='required'/>
                </xs:extension>
            </xs:simpleContent>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>
    <xs:element name='kemprekeys'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence minOccurs='25' maxOccurs='unbounded'>
                <xs:element ref='kpk'/>
            </xs:sequence>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>

    <xs:element name='kpk'>
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:simpleContent>
                <xs:extension base='xs:base64Binary'>
                    <xs:attribute name='id' type='xs:unsignedInt' use='required'/>
                    <xs:attribute name='sig' type='xs:base64Binary' use='required'/>
                </xs:extension>
            </xs:simpleContent>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>
</xs:schema>
]]></code>
    <p>
      Due to the large size brought by ML-KEM-1024, Base85 is the recommended binary-to-text encoding. However, due to
      lack of suitable standardizations in this area, Base64 MUST be used for PUBLIC implementations to maintain
      cross-implementation compatibility. For PRIVATE implementations, it is recommended to use Base85 to save bandwidth
      as is the case for Privt App. <em>Do note that an additional care for XML compatibility MUST be taken care of for
      Base85 to safely work.</em>
    </p>
  </section1>

  <section1 topic='Protobuf Schema' anchor='protobuf-schema'>
    <code><![CDATA[
message PPQMMessage {
    required uint32 n          = 1;
    required uint32 pn         = 2;
    required bytes  dh_pub     = 3;
    optional bytes  ciphertext = 4;
}

message PPQMAuthenticatedMessage {
    required bytes mac     = 1;
    required bytes message = 2; // Byte-encoding of a PPQMMessage
}

message PPQMKeyExchange {
    required uint32 pk_id  = 1;
    required uint32 spk_id = 2;
    required bytes  ik     = 3;
    required bytes  ek     = 4;
    required PPQMAuthenticatedMessage message = 5;
}
]]></code>
  </section1>


  <section1 topic='Acknowledgements' anchor='ack'>
    <p>
      Big thanks to Daniel Gultsch for mentoring the original development of OMEMO. Thanks to the PPQM development team
      for bringing post-quantum security to XMPP, especially for Ron Lauren Hombre's extensive research on the subject.
      Special thanks to the community for their continued support and feedback.
    </p>
  </section1>
</xep>
