<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep><header>
<title>Message Archive Management: Trim Command</title>
<abstract>This specification describes how a client can request "trimming" of an archive</abstract>
&LEGALNOTICE;
<number>xxxx</number>
<status>ProtoXEP</status>
<type>Standards Track</type>
<sig>Standards</sig>
<approver>Council</approver>
<dependencies/>
<supersedes/>
<supersededby/>
<shortname>mamtrim</shortname>
&mwild;
<revision>
<version>0.0.1</version>
<date>2026-03-31</date>
<initials>mjw</initials>
<remark>
</remark>
</revision>
</header>
<section1 topic="Introduction" anchor="intro">

<p>The XMPP ecosystem has standardized around &xep0313; for incoming and outgoing
message synchronization. Messages are stored in the archive for a period of
time, so they can be fetched by all receiving devices. However, the retention
of messages is typically controlled purely by the configuration of the server,
typically as a fixed period of time.</p>

<p>This specification defines a protocol that allows a client to request
"trimming" of an archive’s contents on-demand.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Requirements" anchor="reqs">

<ul>
<li>Allow a client to request trimming of archive items before a certain point</li>
<li>Allow deletion of the entire archive</li>
</ul>

<section2 topic="Intended use cases" anchor="intended-use-cases">

<p>This protocol is designed for on-demand use cases, such as when a user
explicitly requests purging all messages from the archive. It is not designed
for automated client-side enforcement of a general retention policy (e.g.
implementing a user preference that the archive should contain no more than 30
days of messages). Such a feature would be far better implemented with a
server-side enforcement approach, which would allow all clients to discover
and agree on a policy, and function even when clients are offline.</p>

</section2></section1><section1 topic="Use Cases" anchor="usecases">

<section2 topic="Discovering support" anchor="discovering-support">

<p>Servers supporting and allowing this operation MUST advertise the service discovery feature 'urn:xmpp:mamtrim:0'.</p>

<p>If a deployment is configured to disallow trimming (e.g. because of legal or
audit requirements to preserve messages), the feature SHOULD NOT be advertised
to clients.</p>

</section2><section2 topic="Trimming the archive" anchor="trimming-the-archive">

<p>If supported by the server, clients may request for an archive to be 'trimmed' - this means immediate removal of all archived stanzas up to, and including, a specified UID. To ensure archive integrity, it is not possible to remove items from the "middle" or end of an archive.</p>

<p>To request trimming, a client sends an &lt;iq/&gt; of type 'set' to the archive, containing a &lt;trim/&gt; element qualified by the 'urn:xmpp:mamtrim:0' namespace.</p>

<p>An empty &lt;trim/&gt; element requests the deletion of all currently-archived stanzas. Alternatively, the element may contain a single &lt;id/&gt; element which, as character data, specifies the archive UID of an item to trim, along with all older items.</p>

<example  caption="Requesting trim"><![CDATA[<iq type='set' id='gIgQj65M'>
  <trim xmlns='urn:xmpp:mamtrim:0'>
    <id>e5c258ec-2ce4-11f1-841f-507b9dcf344f</id>
  </trim>
</iq>]]></example>

<p>On success, the server returns an empty iq result:</p>

<example  caption="Server returns trim success"><![CDATA[<iq type='result' id='gIgQj65M'></iq>]]></example>

<p>Alternatively, the server returns an appropriate error.</p>

</section2></section1><section1 topic="Business Rules" anchor="rules">

<p>Servers MUST only allow trimming requests from archive owners. For per-user archives, this means the account owner. For group chat archives, this typically means the owner(s) of the group chat.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Accessibility Considerations" anchor="access">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Security Considerations" anchor="security">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="Privacy Considerations" anchor="privacy">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">

<p>None.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="XMPP Registrar Considerations" anchor="registrar">
<section2 topic='Protocol Namespaces' anchor='registrar-ns'>
    <p>This specification defines the following XML namespace:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>urn:xmpp:mamtrim:0</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Upon advancement of this specification from a status of Experimental to a status of Draft, the &REGISTRAR; shall add the foregoing namespace to the registry located at &NAMESPACES;, as described in Section 4 of &xep0053;.</p>
  </section2>

</section1><section1 topic="Design Considerations" anchor="design-considerations">

<p>There were some options for how to specify the cut-off point for trimming:</p>

<ul>
<li>Date/time</li>
<li>ID</li>
</ul>

<p>Both of these can be inclusive (remove items including any with the specified
timestamp or ID) or exclusive (keep the referenced item, but remove earlier
items).</p>

<p>The protocol uses IDs, because it is more precise than timestamps, and the
trim operation is inclusive of the referenced ID. This is because a common
operation is expected to be "trim everything I have received", and this allows
a client to pass the latest ID they have received. This prevents a race
condition in "delete everything" where an incoming message could arrive after
the client sent the request.</p>

</section1><section1 topic="XML Schema" anchor="schema">

<p>TDB.</p>
</section1>
</xep>

